<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rights of the people concerning impositions, stated in a learned argument; with a remonstrance presented to the Kings most excellent Majesty, by the Honorable House of Commons, in the Parliament, An. Dom. 1610. Annoq; Regis Jac. 7. / By a late eminent judge of this nation.</title>
            <author>Whitelocke, James, Sir, 1570-1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96413</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1995C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1647_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2143_3</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867995</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170211</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96413)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170211)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 207:E1647[3], 244:E2143[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rights of the people concerning impositions, stated in a learned argument; with a remonstrance presented to the Kings most excellent Majesty, by the Honorable House of Commons, in the Parliament, An. Dom. 1610. Annoq; Regis Jac. 7. / By a late eminent judge of this nation.</title>
                  <author>Whitelocke, James, Sir, 1570-1632.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 117, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Leak, at the Crown in Fleetstreet, betwixt the two Temple-Gates.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658. [i.e. 1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A late eminent judge of this nation" = Sir James Whitelocke.</note>
                  <note>With two final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Actual publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy E.1647[3]: "Jan: 19"; the 8 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "7"; on Thomason copy 2143[3]: "Feb:".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prerogative, Royal --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170211:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RIGHTS OF THE PEOPLE Concerning IMPOSITIONS, Stated in a learned ARGUMENT; WITH A Remonſtrance preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, by the Honorable Houſe of Commons, in the Parliament, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1610. <hi>Anno<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Regis Jac.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>By a late eminent Judge of this Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Leak,</hi> at the Crown in Fleetſtreet, betwixt the two Temple-Gates. 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170211:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170211:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Courteous READER.</head>
            <p>THis excellent Treatiſe of the no leſs worthy Author, happily falling into my hands, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly thought it my duty to make that publick, which had given ſo much uſeful ſatisfaction to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny learned, and judicious, in private; remembring that antient Adage, <hi>Bonum quò communius, eò praeſtantius</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope it is needleſs to commend either the Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end Author deceaſed, the Treatiſe, its uſe, or ſtile; ſince the Authority by which it is publiſhed, is a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient argument of their known worth.</p>
            <p>If thou kindly accept of his good meaning, whoſe onely aim in the publiſhing hereof was the Common good, it will be an encouragement to him (and others) to preſent to thy view, what may hereafter fall into his hands worthy thy further peruſal.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine;</hi> J. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:170211:3"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>20. <hi>Maii.</hi> 1641.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>AT a Committee appointed by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe of Commons, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of Books, and of the licencing and ſuppreſſing of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is Ordered, That this Treatiſe be publiſhed in Print.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sir <hi>Edward Deering,</hi> Kt. and Baronet.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>☞ <hi>There is lately come forth, An exact Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Records in the Tower of</hi> London, <hi>from the reign of King</hi> Edward <hi>the Second, unto</hi> Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard <hi>the Third, of all the Parliaments holden in each Kings reign, and the ſeveral Acts in every Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, together with the Names and Titles of all the Dukes, Marqueſſes, Earls, Viſcounts and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons ſummoned to every of the ſaid Parliaments. Collected by Sir</hi> Robert Cotton, <hi>Knight and Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. And are to be ſold by</hi> William Leak <hi>at the Crown in Fleetstreet, betwixt the two Temple gates.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="remonstrance">
            <pb facs="tcp:170211:3"/>
            <head>A Remonſtrance delivered to His Majeſty in writing, after the inhibition given by Him to the Commons Houſe of Parliament, aſwell by word of mouth, as by Letters, not to proceed in the examining his Right to Impoſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out aſſent of Parliament.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty. </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt gracious Sovereign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas we your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt humble Subjects, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have received firſt by meſſage, and ſince by ſpeech from your Majeſty a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of reſtraint, from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating
<pb facs="tcp:170211:4"/>in Parliament your Majeſties right of Impoſing upon your Subjects goods exported, or imported out of, or into this Realm; yet allowing us to examine the grievance of theſe Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in regard of quantity, time, and other circumſtances of diſproportion thereto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident: We your ſaid hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Subjects nothing doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but that your Majeſty had no intent by that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to infringe the antient and fundamental right of the Liberty of Parliament in point of exact diſcuſſing of all matters concerning them, and their poſſeſſions, goods, and
<pb facs="tcp:170211:4"/>rights whatſoever, which yet we cannot but conceive to be done in effect by this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, do with all humble du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty make this Remonſtrance unto your Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We hold it an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, general and undoubted right of Parliament, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate freely all matters which do properly concern the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and his right or eſtate; which freedom of debate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once fore-cloſed, the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the liberty of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is withthal diſſolved.</p>
            <p>And whereas in this caſe the Subjects right on the one ſide, and your Majeſties Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives on the other, cannot
<pb facs="tcp:170211:5"/>poſſibly be ſevered in debate of either: We alledge that your Majeſties Prerogatives of that kinde concerning di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly the Subjects right and intereſt, are daily handled and diſcuſſed in all Courts at <hi>Weſtminster,</hi> and have been ever freely debated upon all fit occaſions, both in this and all other former Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments, without reſtraint; which being forbidden, it is impoſſible for the Subject, either to know, or to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Right and Propriety to his own Lands and Goods, though never ſo juſt and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</p>
            <p>It may further pleaſe your
<pb facs="tcp:170211:5"/>moſt excellent Majeſty to underſtand, that we have no minde to impugn, but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire to inform our ſelves of your Highneſs Prerogative in that point, which (if ever) is now moſt neceſſary to be known; and though it were to no other purpoſe, yet to ſatisfie the generality of your Majeſties Subjects, who finding themſelves much grieved by theſe new Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, do languiſh in much ſorrow and diſcomfort</p>
            <p>Theſe Reaſons (Dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign) being the proper Reaſons of Parliament, do plead for the upholding of this our antient Right and
<pb facs="tcp:170211:6"/>Liberty. Howbeit ſeeing it hath pleaſed your Majeſty to inſiſt upon that Judgment in the Exchequer, as being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ſufficient for us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further examination: Upon great deſire of leaving your Majeſty unſatisfied in no one point of one of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and proceedings, We profeſs touching that Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we neither do nor will take upon us to reverſe it; but our deſire is to know the Reaſons whereupon the ſame was grounded; and the rather for that a general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit is had, That the Reaſons of that Judgement may be extended much further, even
<pb facs="tcp:170211:6"/>to the utter ruine of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient liberty of this Kingdom, and of your Subjects Right of propriety to their Goods and Lands.</p>
            <p>Then for the Judgment it ſelf, being the firſt and laſt that ever was given in that kind (for ought appearing unto us,) and being onely in one Caſe, and againſt one man, it can binde in law no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but that perſon; and is alſo reverſible by Writ of error granted heretofore by Act of Parliament; and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he nor any other Subject is debarred by it, from trying his Right in the ſame or like caſe, in any of your Majeſties
<pb facs="tcp:170211:7"/>Courts of Record at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, We nothing doubt, but our intended proceeding in a full examination of the right, nature, and meaſure of theſe new Impoſitions (if this reſtraint had not come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween) ſhould have been ſo orderly and ſo moderately carried and imployed to the manifold neceſſities of theſe times, and given your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ſo true a view of the ſtate and right of your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that it would have been much to your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres content and ſatisfaction, (which we moſt deſire,) and removed all cauſes of fears
<pb facs="tcp:170211:7"/>and jealouſies from the loyal hearts of your Subjects, which is (as it ought to be) our care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful endeavour: Whereas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe in that other way di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by your Majeſty, we cannot ſafely proceed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out concluding for ever the right of the Subject, which without due examination thereof we may not do.</p>
            <p>We therefore your loyal and dutiful Commons; not ſwerving from the approved ſteps of our Anceſtors, moſt humbly and inſtantly beſeech your gracious Majeſty, that without offence to the ſame, we may according to the undoubted Right and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb facs="tcp:170211:8"/>of Parliament, proceed in our intended courſe of a full examination of theſe Impoſitions; That ſo we may chearfully paſs on to your Majeſties buſineſs, from which this ſtop hath by diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſo long with-held us. And we your Majeſties moſt humble, faithful, and loyal Subjects, ſhall ever (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our bounden du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) pray for your Majeſties long and happy reign over us.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170211:8"/>
            <head>The queſtion is, whether the King, without aſſent of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, may ſet impoſitions upon the wares and goods of merchants exported, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, out of, and into this Realme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hree things have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated in this Parliament, that have much concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the right of our whole Nation, of which every one of them hath exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the other by a gradation in weight and moment.</p>
            <p>The firſt, was the change of our name, which was a point of honour, wherein we ſhewed our ſelves not willing to leave
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170211:9"/>that name, by which our anceſtors made our Nation famous:
<note place="margin">The name of Britaine not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in legall proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</note> yet have we loſt it, ſaving onely in thoſe caſes where our ancient and faithfull Protector, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law doth retaine it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was the union; a queſtion of greater moment, for that concerned the freehold of our whole Nation, not in ſo high a point as having, or not having; but in point of Diviſion and participation, that is, whether we ſhould enjoy the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and liberties of the kingdome our ſelves onely as we and our anceſtors have done, or admit our neighbour Nation to have equall right in them, and ſo make our own part the leſs, by how much the greater number ſhould be among whom the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion was to be made.
<note place="margin">Coke <hi>l.</hi> 7. Calvins caſe.</note> This was adjudged againſt us both Legally and Solemnly, and therefore in that we reſt, hoping of that effect of this judgement which we read of in the Poet,
<q xml:lang="lat">Tros Tyriuſque mihi nullo diſcrimine habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.
<note place="margin">Virgil. Aen. l. 1. Dido's <hi>ſpeech to</hi> Aeneas.</note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The third is the queſtion now in hand, which exceedeth the other two in impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170211:9"/>&amp; conſequence, concerning the whole kingdome; for it is a queſtion of our very eſſence, not what we ſhall be called, nor how we ſhall divide that we have, but whether we ſhall have any thing or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: for if there be a right in the King to alter the property of that which is ours without our conſent, we are but te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants at his will of that which we have. If it be in the King and Parliament, Then have we propertie, and are Tenants at our own will: for that which is done in Parliament, is done by all our wills and conſents. And this is the very ſtate of the queſtion which is propoſed, that is, whether the King may impoſe without conſent of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Impoſitions are of two natures, <hi>Forreine,</hi> and <hi>Inteſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inteſtine, be thoſe which are raiſed within our land in the commerce and deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that is at home within our ſelves, and may aſwell for that reaſon be ſo call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as for that <hi>veſcuntur inteſtinis Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicae,</hi> They are fed and nouriſhed with the conſuming and waſting of the entralls of the Common wealth. Againſt theſe I need not to ſpeake; for the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170211:10"/>Kings learned Councell have with great honour and conſcience in full Councell acknowledged them to be againſt the law.</p>
            <p>Therefore I will apply my ſelf to ſpeak of impoſitions forreigne, being the ſingle queſtion now in hand, and maintained on the Kings behalfe with great art and eloquence.</p>
            <p>The inconvenience of theſe impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Common-wealth, that is, how hurtfull they are to the Merchants, in impoveriſhing them in their eſtates; to the King in the increaſing of his reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues by decay of traffique, and to the whole people in making all commodities exceſſive deare, is confeſſed by all, and therefore need no debate. The point of right is now only in queſtion, and of that I will ſpeak with conſcience and integrity, rather deſirous that the truth may be knowne, and right be done, than that the opinion of my ſelf or any other may prevaile.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of this queſtion was given by the book of rates lately ſet out, affronted with the copy of Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, dated <hi>July</hi> 28.6. <hi>Jac.</hi> In
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170211:10"/>which book, beſides the rates, is ſet down every kind of merchandiſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and imported, for the true anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſubſidy to the King, according to the Statute of Tonnage and Poundage.</p>
            <p>In the firſt yeare of his reigne there is an addition of impoſitions upon all thoſe kind of wares, which within the book are expreſſed, and the rate of the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition as high and in ſome caſes higher than the rate of the ſubſidy: And this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be by authority of thoſe Letters Patents. Hereupon conſidering with my ſelfe, that heretofore the ſetting on of one only impoſition without aſſent of Parliament, upon ſome one kinde of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, and that for a ſmall time, and upon urgent neceſſity of actuall war, did ſo affect our whole Nation, and eſpecially the great Councel of the Parliament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Repreſentative body of the whole Common-wealth, that neither the ſun did ſhine, nor the rivers run their courſes until it was taken off by the publick judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the whole State.</p>
            <p>I thought it concerned me, and other members of that Councell, that were no leſs truſted for our Countrey,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170211:11"/>than thoſe in former times, and have their actions to guide and direct us, to have the ſame care they had in preſerving the right and liberties of the people, having now more cauſe then they had, for that the impoſitions now ſet on without aſſent of Parliament, are not upon one or two ſpeciall kinds of goods, but almoſt inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite upon all, and do extend to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of many hundreds, as appeareth by that printed book of rates, and are ſet in charge upon the whole kingdome as an inheritance to continue to the King, his heires and ſucceſſors for ever: which limitation of eſtate in matter of impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was never heard of, nor read of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as I conceive.</p>
            <p>The inducements expreſſed in theſe Letters Patents are much upon point of State, and with reference to the rights and practice of fortaine Princes; For this I will not take upon me to enter into the conſideration of ſuch great myſteries of policie, and government, but will only put you in minde of that I obſerve out of <hi>Tit.
<note place="margin">Tit. Liv. l. 8.</note> Livius</hi> the Romane <hi>Hiſtoriographer: <q xml:lang="lat">Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem divini humanique moris memoriam abolemus, cum nova peregrinaque patriis &amp; priſcis praeferimus.</q>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170211:11"/>
            <p>To that which hath been ſpoken for the Kings Prerogative, I will give anſwer to ſo much of it as I may conveniently in my paſſage through this debate: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I will principally endeavor to give ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to ſuch new objections as were made by the worthie and learned Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor of the King that ſpake laſt, in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his Majeſties Prerogative.</p>
            <p>The caſe in termes is this:
<note place="margin">Pat. July 28. <hi>Iac.</hi> 6.</note> The King by his Letters Patents before recited, hath ordained willed, and commanded that theſe new impoſitions contained in that book of rates ſhall be for ever hereafter payd unto him, his Heires, and Succeſſors, upon paine of his diſpleaſure: Hereupon the queſtion ariſeth whether by this Edict and Ordinance ſo made by the King himſelfe, by his Letters Patents of his own will and power abſolute, without aſſent of Parliament, he be ſo lawfully intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to that he doth impoſe, as that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he doth alter the property of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects goods, and is enabled to recover theſe impoſition, by courſe of Law.</p>
            <p>I think he cannot; and I ground my opinion upon theſe foure reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is againſt the naturall frame and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170211:12"/>conſtitution of the policie of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which is <hi>jus publicum regni,</hi> and ſo ſubverteth the fundamentall Law of the Realme, and induceth a new forme of ſtate and government.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is againſt the municipall Law of the Land, which is <hi>jus privatum,</hi> the Law of property and of private right.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is againſt divers Statutes made to reſtraine our King in this point.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is againſt the practice and action of our Common wealth, <hi>contra morem majorum;</hi> and this is the modeſteſt rule to limit both Kings Prerogatives, and Subjects Liberties.</p>
            <p>Upon the firſt, and fourth of theſe foure principal grounds I will more inſiſt then upon the ſecond and third, both for that in their own nature they are a more proper matter for a Councel of State, to the judgement of which I apply my diſcourſe (and they have not been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced by others:) As alſo for that the other two (as more fit for a barre, and the Courts of ordinary juſtice) have by ſome profeſſors of the Law been already moſt leardnedly and exquiſitely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170211:12"/>
            <p>For the firſt: it will be admitted for a rule, and ground of State, that in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Common-wealth and government there be ſome rights of Soveraignty, <hi>jura Majeſtatis,</hi> which regularly, and of common right doe belong to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign power of that State; unleſs Cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome, or the proviſional ordinance of that State doe otherwiſe diſpoſe of them: which Soveraigne power is <hi>poteſtas ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> a power that can controule all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther powers, and cannot be controuled but by it ſelf</p>
            <p>It will not be denied that the power of impoſing hath ſo great a truſt in It, by reaſon of the miſchiefes may grow to the Common-wealth by the abuſes of it, that it hath ever been ranked among thoſe rights of Soveraign power.</p>
            <p>Then is there no further queſtion to be made but to examine where the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne power is in this Kingdome; for there is the right of impoſition.</p>
            <p>The Soveraigne power is agreed to be in the King: but in the King is a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold power; the one in Parliament, as he is aſſiſted with the conſent of the whole State; the other out of Parliament as he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170211:13"/>is ſole, and ſingular, guided merely by his own will. And if of theſe two powers in the King, one is greater than the other, and can direct and controule the other; that is <hi>Suprema Poteſtas,</hi> the Soveraigne power, and the other is <hi>ſubordinata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will then be eaſily proved, that the power of the King in Parliament is greater than his power out of Parliament, and doth rule and controule it; for if the King make a grant by his Letters Patents out of Parliament, it bindeth him and his ſucceſſors, he cannot revoke it, nor any of his Succeſſours; But by his power in Parliament he may defeate and avoyd it; and therefore that is the greater power.</p>
            <p>If a judgement be given in the Kings Bench, by the King himſelfe (as may be, and by the Law is intended) a writ of Error, to reverſe this judgement, may be ſued before the King in Parliament, which writ muſt be granted by the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, upon bill indorſed by the King himſelf,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>H.</hi> 7.19 6. Lib. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trac. fol. 302. c. 1.</note> as the book is 1 <hi>H,</hi> 7.19.6. And the forme of the writ of Error is, that it being directed to the Chiefe Juſtice of the Kings Bench, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Quia in recordo &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſu,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170211:13"/>ac etiam in redditione judicii loquelae, quae ſuit in Curiâ noſtrâ coram nobis, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror intervenit manifeſtus ad grave dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp;c. Nos errorem (ſi quis fuerit) modo debito corrigi, &amp; partibus praedictas plenam &amp; celerem juſtitiam fieri volentes, in hàc parte vobis mandamus, quòa Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordum &amp; proceſſum loquelae illius cum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ea tangentibus, in praeſens Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum noſtrum ſub ſigillio tuo diſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>è &amp; apertè mittas &amp; hoc breve, ut inspectis, &amp;c. nos de Conſilio &amp; adviſamento Domi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norum ſpiritualium &amp; temporal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um, ac Communitatis in Parliamento noſtro prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto exiſtentis, ulterius pro errore illo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigendo fieri faciamus quod de jure &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum legem &amp; conſuetudinem Regni noſtri Angliae fuerit faciendum.</hi>
               </q> So you ſee the Appeal is from the King out of the Parliament, to the King in Parliament; the writ is in his name; the rectifying and correcting the errours is by him, but with the aſſent of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
<note place="margin">The booke is not ſo, that the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons ſhould meddle.</note> than which there can be no ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger evidence to prove, that his power out of Parliament is ſubordinate to his power in Parliament; for in Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, be they lawes, grounds, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170211:14"/>elſe, the Act and power is the Kings, but with the aſſent of the Lords and Commons, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it the moſt ſoveraigne and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame power above all, and controul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by none. Beſides this right of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, there be others in the Kingdome of the ſame nature: As the power to make lawes; the power of Naturalization; the power of erection of arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; the power to judge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out appeale; the power to legitimate: all which do belong to the King only in in Parliament. Others there be of the ſame nature, that the King may exerciſe out of Parliament, which right is grown unto him in them, more in thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by the uſe and practice of the Common-wealth: as denization, coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, making warr: which power the King hath time out of minde practiſed, without the gain-ſaying and murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his ſubjects: But theſe other powers before mentioned have ever been executed by him in Parliament, and not otherwiſe, but with the reluctation of the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Can any man give me a reaſon, why
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170211:14"/>the King can only in Parliament make lawes? No man ever read any law whereby it was ſo ordained; and yet no man ever read that any King practiſed the contrary: Therefore it is the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall right of the Kingdome, and the very natural conſtitution of our State and policy, being one of the higheſt rights of Soveraigne power: So it is in natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralization, legitimation, and the reſt of that ſort before recited.</p>
            <p>It hath been alleaged that thoſe which in this Cauſe have enforced their reaſons from this Maxime of ours <hi>(That the King cannot alter the Law)</hi> have diverted from the queſtion.</p>
            <p>I ſay under favor they have not; for that in effect is the very queſtion now in hand; for if he alone out of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may impoſe, he altereth the Law of England in one of theſe two maine fundamental points. He muſt either take his Subjects goods from them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out aſſent of the party, which is againſt the Law; or elſe he muſt give his own Letters Pattents the force of a Law, to alter the property of his Subjects goods, which is alſo againſt the Law.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170211:15"/>
            <p>That the King of England cannot take his ſubjects goods, without their conſent, it need not be proved more than a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; it is <hi>jus indigenae,</hi> an old homeborne right, declared to be Law by divers ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Realme:
<note place="margin">34 <hi>E.</hi> 3. c. 2.</note> As in 34. <hi>E.</hi> 3. cap 2. That no office of the Kings, or of his heires, ſhall take any goods of any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſon without the aſſent and good will of the party, to whom the goods belonged. The ſame is declared in many other Statutes made againſt priſages and purveyances. Neither have ever any Kings attempted to go plainly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt that right, but have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed certaine legal colours and ſhadowes for their wrongfull doing in that kind, which I doe find were of three ſorts:
<note place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, Loans or Privie Seales, Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</note> by way of Commiſſion; by way of Loan; by way of Benevolence Commiſſions of all other were the moſt inſolent; for they went out (as it were by authority to levy ayd of the people upon great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the Commonwealth.) Theſe were condemned in Parliament. 21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Num.</hi> 16. upon a grevious complaint made of the uſe of them by the Commons, unto the King in Parliament: wherein
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170211:15"/>the people doe pray the King, that he would be pleaſed to remember how at the Parliament held the 17 year of his raign, and at the laſt Parliament,
<note place="margin">That is, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> it was then accorded, and granted by their ſaid Lord the King and his Councell, that there ſhould goe out no Commiſſions out of Chauncery for Hobbeleries, Archers, and other charges to be levied upon the people, if they were not granted in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; which ordinances were not obſerved: by reaſon whereof the people were impoveriſhed aed decayed, for which they prayed the King that he would be pleaſed to take pity of his people, and the ordinances and grants made to his people in Parliament to affirme and hold; And that if ſuch Commiſſions goe out without aſſent of Parliament, that the Commons, which are grieved thereby, may have writs of <hi>ſuperſedeas,</hi> according to the ſaid Ordinance, and that the people be not bound to obey them.</p>
            <p>To this the Kings anſwer is.</p>
            <q xml:lang="frm">
               <hi>Si ul tiel impoſition fuit fait per grand neceſſitie, &amp; ceo del aſſent des Prelates,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170211:16"/>Countes, Barons, &amp; aut grandes &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes des Commons adon<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> preſents, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant moins noſtre Seignior le Roy ne voet que tiel impoſition non duement fait, ſoit treit in conſequence, eins voet que les ordinances dont ceſt petition fait mention ſoit blenment garoes.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The laſt time that ever King attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that courſe of exaction was 17 <hi>H.</hi> 8.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stowes</hi> annals. 17. <hi>H.</hi> 8.</note> upon the taking of the French King at <hi>Pavia,</hi> by the forces of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth: Cardinal <hi>Wolſey</hi> having a purpoſe to put the King into a warre about that quarrell, and finding his cophers empty, adviſed this way, to ſend out Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, and by them to levie ayd of the people, according to the value of their eſtate; But this gave ſuch diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to the whole Realme, that it cauſed in many places an actuall rebellion: and the Cardinal being called to give an account of this bad advice, did juſtifie this fact by the example ot <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who adviſed <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to take the fifth part of his ſubjects goods: But when he ſaw that would not ſerve the turne,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170211:16"/>he falſely laid it upon the Judges, inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King, he did it by their advice, being reſolved by them of the lawfulneſs of the fact. So you ſee that great Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men found more ſafety in matter of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of our Commonwealth, in making a falſe report of a point of the Common Law, then in a true Text of the Scripture. And if any Church men will endeavour by application of the Text of Scripture, to overthrow the antient Law and Liberties of the Kingdom, I would adviſe them to be admoniſhed by the ill ſucceſs of the Cardinal, in this particular action, and by the miſerable cataſtrophe of his whole life and fortunes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Loans and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Seals.</note> Loans and Appreſts were thoſe which we call Privy Seals, which though they were more moderate in ſhew, yet being made againſt the good will of the parties, were as injurous indeed as the other. The Commons in Parliament, 25. <hi>E</hi> 3. <hi>Num.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rot. pat. 25. <hi>E</hi> 3. <hi>num.</hi> 16.</note> 16. made a grievous complaint to the King againſt the uſe of them, and prayed, that none from thenceforth ſhould be compelled to make Loans againſt their will, and they gave this reaſon, in their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for that it is againſt reaſon, and the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170211:17"/>franchiſe of the land, and prayed that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitntion might be made to thoſe that have made ſuch Loans.</p>
            <p>To this the Kings reſcript was; <hi>It pleaſeth our Lord the King it be ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<note place="margin">Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</note> Came in thoſe kinde of exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which were termed by the fair name of <hi>Benevolences;</hi> but they became ſo odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as they gave the occaſion of a good Law to be made againſt themſelves, and againſt all other ſhifts, and devices, by what new terms ſoever impoſed upon the Subjects:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>R.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2</note> the Law is, 1 <hi>R.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2 and is thus; The King remembring how the Commons of this his Realm, by new and unlawful inventions, and inordinate co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetiſe, againſt the Law of this Realm, have been put to great ſervitude and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant charges and exactions, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by a new Impoſition called a <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence,</hi> enacteth by the adviſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that the Subjects and Commons of this Land from henceforth ſhall in no wiſe be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by any ſuch charges, or impoſitions called the <hi>Benevolence,</hi> nor by ſuch like thing.</p>
            <p>But if you will deny, that the King doth in this caſe take the goods of his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170211:17"/>Subject without his aſſent, then you muſt other fall upon mine alternative propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That the Kings Patent hath in this caſe the power of a Law, to alter property; for how can he recover the impoſed by a legal courſe of proceeding, and by judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his Court, but upon a title pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent him, before the action brought, which title muſt be a property in the ſame impoſed? and how commeth he by that property, but by his own Letters Patents, by which he declareth he will have that ſame as an impoſition? For the Judgment giveth not the right, but onely doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and declare it, and giveth executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it: So in this point the queſtion is, whether the Kings Patent hath the force and power of the Law, or not; for if it be not maintained that it hath, it can never be concluded that he can tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the property of his Subjects goods to himſelf, without the aſſent of them; for <hi>quod meum eſt, ſine facto meo alterius fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri non poteſt.</hi> And if you give this power to the Kings Patent, you ſubject the Law, and take away all rules and bounds of ſettled government, and leave in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject no property of his own, neither do
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170211:18"/>you by this advance the Kings power and prerogatjve,
<note place="margin">Bracton, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> but you make him no King; for as <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaith, <q>
                  <hi>Rex eſt ubi domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur lex, non voluntas.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So we ſee that the power of impoſing, and power of making Laws are <hi>convertibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia &amp; coincidentia;</hi> and whoſoever can do the one, can do the other; And this was the opinion of Sir <hi>John Forteſcue</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend and honorable Judge, a very learned profeſſor of the Common Law, and Chief Juſtice of the Kings Bench,
<note place="margin">Forteſc. <hi>de laudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Leg. Ang. c.</hi> 9.</note> in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> 6. His words are theſe in his Book, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>De laudibus Legum Angliae, cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Non poteſt Rex Angliae ad libitum leges mutare regni ſui; principatu namque nedum regali, ſed &amp; politico ipſe domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: Si regali tantum praeeſſet iis, leges mutare poſſet; tallagia quoque, &amp; caetera onera imponere, ipſis inconſultis, quale do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minium leges civiles indicant, cum dicunt quod principi placuerit, legis habet vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem; ſed longè aliter poteſt Rex politicis imperans, quia nec leges ipſe ſine ſubdito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aſſenſu mutare poterit, nec ſubjectum populum renitentem onerare peregrinis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitionibus.</hi>
               </q> In which place I muſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret unto you, that <hi>peregrinae impoſitiones</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170211:18"/>be not ſtrange and unheard of impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as was urged by the worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that ſpake laſt; but impoſitions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on traffick into, and out of forain Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
<note place="margin">Forteſc. <hi>de laud. Leg. Ang. cap.</hi> 36.</note> which is the very thing in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Further in the thirty ſixth Chapter, he ſaith of the King of <hi>England, <q xml:lang="lat">Neque Rex ibidem per ſe aut miniſtros ſuos talla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia, Subſidia, aut alia quaevis onera impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit ligeis ſuis, aut leges corum mutat, vel novas condit, ſine conceſſione vel aſſenſu to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius regni ſui in Parliamento.</q>
               </hi> So he maketh theſe two powers of making Law, and impoſing to be concomitant in the ſame hand, and that the one of them is not without the other; he giveth the ſame reaſon for this, as we do now, but in other words, becauſe (as he ſaith) in <hi>England</hi> it is <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>principatus mixtus, &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticus,</hi>
               </q> the King hath his ſoveraign pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in Parliament, aſſiſted and ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the conſent of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and therefore theſe powers are to be exerciſed by him only in Parliament. In other Countries they admit the ground of the Civil Law, <hi>quod principi placuerit, legis habet vigorem;</hi> Becauſe they have an abſolute power to make Law, they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170211:19"/>have alſo a power to impoſe, which hath the force of a Law in transferring pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty.
<note place="margin">Ph. Com. <hi>l</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. l. 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>Philip Comines,</hi> that lived at that time, in his fourth Book, the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the fifth Book the eighth Chapter, taketh notice of this policy of <hi>England,</hi> and commends it above all other States, as ſettled in moſt ſecurity: And further to our purpoſe laieth this ground, That a King cannot take one penny from his Subjects without their conſent, but it is violence. And you may there note the miſchiefs that grew to the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> by the voluntary impoſitions firſt brought in by <hi>Charles</hi> the Seventh, and ever ſince continued, and encreaſed to the utter impoveriſhment of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, and the loſs of their free Councel of three Eſtates: And if this power of impoſing were quietly ſetled in our Kings, conſidering what the greateſt uſe they make of aſſembling of Parliaments, which is the ſupply of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, I do not ſee any likelihood to hope for often meetings in that kind, becauſe they would provide themſelves by that other means. And thus much for my firſt reaſon grounded upon the natural conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170211:19"/>of the Policy of our Kingdom, and the publike Right of our Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For the point of Common Law,
<note place="margin">Com. Law.</note> which is my ſecond reaſon, it hath been well debated, and nothing left unſpoken that can be ſaid in it; and therefore I will decline to ſpeak of that, which other men have well diſcuſſed, and the rather, for that there is nothing in our Law-book directly, and in point of this matter; neither is the word <hi>(impoſition)</hi> found in them, until the caſe in my L. <hi>Dier.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">Diec. 1. E. 165.</note> 
               <hi>Eliz.</hi> 165. for we ſhall finde this buſineſs of an higher ſtrain, and alwaies handled elſewhere, as afterwards ſhall appear: yet I will offer ſome Anſwers to ſuch Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections as have been made on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in point of Common Law, and have not been much ſtood upon by others to be anſwered.</p>
            <p>The Objections that have been made are theſe; That from the firſt Book of the Law to the laſt, no man ever read any thing againſt the Kings power of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing: No Judgement was ever given againſt it, in any of the Kings Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> Other points of Prerogative as high as this, diſputed and debated, his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170211:20"/>exceſs in them limited,
<note place="margin">42. Aſſ. p. 9.</note> as in the book of 42. <hi>Aſſ. pl.</hi> 5. where the Judges took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a Commiſſion from one that had power given by it to him under the great Seal, to take ones perſon, and to ſeiſe his goods before he was indicted: So Maſter <hi>Scrogs</hi> caſe.
<note place="margin">1, <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>E.</hi> Dier. 175</note> 1, <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>El Dier.</hi> 175 the power of the King in making a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to determine a queſtion of right, depending between two parties notably debated, and ruled againſt the King, that he could not grant it.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, That caſes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (of which the queſtion now handled is) have ever been taken to be of that extraordinary conſequence, in point of the Common right of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that the States would never truſt any of the Courts of ordinary Juſtice with the deciding of them; but aſſumed the cogniſance of them unto the high Court of Parliament, as the fitteſt place to decide matters ſo much concerning the whole body of the Kingdom, as 2. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.7. it appears that <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. had granted a Charter to the men of Great <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> that all the ſhips of Merchants, coming to the Port of <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> ſhould land
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170211:20"/>their goods at their Haven, and not at any other Haven at that Port, as at <hi>Garne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> and Little <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> which were members of that Port. This was very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient for the Merchants, and a great hurt to Traffick, and therefore the Charter was queſtioned in the time of <hi>Ed</hi> 2. and adjudged good by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil: But the parties not contented with this judgment, in the ſecond year of King <hi>E.</hi> 3. by an order in Parliament made upon a Petition there exhibited againſt this Grant, brought a <hi>Scire facias</hi> out of the Chancery returnable in the Kings Bench, to queſtion again the lawfulneſs of the Patent, and in that Suit the cauſe was notably debated, and thoſe Reaſons much inſiſted upon that have been enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in this caſe; as that of the Kings power in the cuſtody of the Ports: But the matter ſo depending in the ordinary Court of Juſtice, a Writ came out of the Parliament, and did adjourn it thither again; where it gave occaſion of a good Law to be made to prevent the like Grants, and to make them void notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any Judgment given upon them, and to make ſuch Judgments alſo void.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170211:21"/>The Statute is, 9: <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. And in the Parliament Rolls,
<note place="margin">9. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. Every Alien and Denizen may carry his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe where it pleaſeth him, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any Charter granted, or Judgment thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 16, &amp; 17. R. 2.</note> 2 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>num</hi> 109. we finde a notable Record, which gives warrant for the proceeding in Parliament, in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as hath been in this Caſe, notwithſtanding the Judgment in the Exchequer, and declares to the Kingdom, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the great wonder made by ſome men, nothing hath been done in this buſineſs by thoſe that ſerve in the Parliament, but in imitation of their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Predeceſſors in the like caſe. In the ſecond year of <hi>H.</hi> 4. the Commons ſhew that in the time of <hi>R.</hi> 2. by the means of <hi>John Waltham,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>England,</hi> wrongfully, without au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament, and by reaſon of a Judgement given in the Exchequer, 16, <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. <hi>R.</hi> 2. by the Barons there, againſt certain Merchants of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and other places, paſſage had been taken for Wines otherwiſe then in ancient times had been, and therefore they prayed, they might pay their priſe Wines in the manner they had uſed to pay, notwithſtanding any
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170211:21"/>Judgment given in the Exchequer, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ordinance made by the ſaid Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, contrary to the antient uſage; which Petition the King granted, and the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereupon became void, and the priſage Wine hath been paid contrary to the Judgment ever ſince.</p>
            <p>In 1. <hi>El. Dier.</hi> 165.
<note place="margin">1. El. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. 265.</note> upon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, made by the Merchants, of the impoſitions ſet upon Cloth by Queen <hi>Mary</hi> by her abſolute power without aſſent of Parliament; The Cauſe was thought too weighty to be decided in any one Court; but (as it appeareth in the Book) it was referred to all the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> who divers times had conference about it. So it may well be, there is nothing againſt it in our year Books, for there is nothing of it.</p>
            <p>Another Objection was this, which was made in the laſt argument, <hi>viz.</hi> That Cuſtom is originally due by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of <hi>England;</hi> it can then have no other ground or cauſe, but meerly by the Kings royal Prerogative, as a right and duty originally belonging to his Crown: which if it be, it muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow he may impoſe, for that is but
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170211:22"/>the exerciſing of that right. To prove this was alleadged the caſe 39.
<note place="margin">39 E. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3.13. by which caſe it appeareth, that King <hi>John</hi> had a Cuſtom of eight pence on a Tun of Wine in the Port of <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampton,</hi> but the Book doth not tell you that the King had it by prerogative, and he might have it as well otherwiſe; as by preſcription, or convention, which ſhall rather be intended, by reaſon of the certainty of the ſum paied; for if it were by prerogative, he might take ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more, ſometimes leſs at his will, the right being indefinite, and the quantity limited onely by his own diſcretion. A common perſon may have ſuch a cuſtom certain, as 18. <hi>El Dier.</hi> 352. The Mayor of <hi>London</hi> hath the twentieth part of Salt brought into the City by Aliens,
<note place="margin">18 El. Dier. 352</note> which is a great Impoſition, but is good by preſcription originally, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived greater ſtrength ſince, by Acts of Parliament made for the confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Liberties and Cuſtoms of the City of <hi>London.</hi> So it appeareth that <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Britain</hi> had Cuſtom of the ſhips that arrived at his Port of Little <hi>Yarmouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dier. 43.</note> worth twenty pounds <hi>per annum.</hi> And
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170211:22"/>theſe inſtances do inefer, that a Cuſtom may be otherwiſe then by prerogative, and therefore it is no good argument to conclude, the King had ſuch a cuſtom, Therefore he had it by Prerogative.</p>
            <p>The Book in 30. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Dier.</hi> 43.
<note place="margin">30 Hen. 8 Dier. 43.</note> was much preſſed on this point, which ſaith that Cuſtom belonged to the King at Common Law, and doth inſtance in Wooll, Wooll-fells, and Leather begun at the Common Law, but abridged by the Statute of 14 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ca</hi> 21. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">14 Ed. 3. <hi>c.</hi> 21. <hi>ſtat.</hi>
               </note> but this appeareth to be a great error, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaking in the Book; for we do finde that that Cuſtom of Woolls, Wooll-fells and Leather was begun by a Grant in Parliament, as appeareth in Statute 15 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. The words be granted to us by the Commonalty aforeſaid; and the laſt mention before was that the King had granted to the Biſhops, Earls, Barons, and all the Commonalty of the Land, <hi>&amp;c. Novemb.</hi> 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. The Kingrecited in his Letter Patents That <hi>Prelati, magnates ac tota communitas mercatorum Regni,</hi> granted this new Cuſtom. And ſo the ground and motive of that opinion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing falſe all grounded upon that muſt needs be erroneous.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170211:23"/>
            <p>It was objected, That the King hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at this day the encreaſe of four pence in the pound, over due Cuſtom, paid by Merchants Aliens according to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the <hi>Charta mercatoria</hi> 31 <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rot. char. 31. E. 1. <hi>num.</hi> 42. in Turri.</note> 1. by meer right of Prerogative at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law; for by that Grant of the Merchants he cannot hold it, they being no Body Politick at the time of the Grant; and therefore the Grant is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly void to binde in ſucceſſion, and yet the Merchants Aliens do pay it at this day.</p>
            <p>It is agreed, That by the Common Law a contract with a number not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate, bindeth not ſucceſſion; but we muſt take notice, that they by whom that Grant was made, of the augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Cuſtom, by three pence in the pound, and other encreaſes, 31. <hi>E.</hi> 1. were Merchants Aliens, who by the Law of Merchants, and Nations may contract to bind their ſucceſſors in matters of Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick: For their contracts are not ruled by the Common Law of the Land, but by the Law of Nations, <hi>&amp; per legem Mercatoriam,</hi> as the Book caſe is, 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.10. and there was a good conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170211:23"/>given them by the King for this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Cuſtom: as diſcharge of priſe Wines for two ſhillings the Tun, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Immunities, which all Merchants A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liens hold and enjoy at this day, by force of that contract made, 31 <hi>E.</hi> 1. For a ſtranger paieth now but two ſhillings the Tun for priſage, whereas it ſtandeth an Engliſhman in much more; ſo as the rule of commutative Juſtice maketh the contract available to the King againſt the Merchants, becauſe he parteth with part of his priſage to the Merchant, and maketh it available to the Merchant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, becauſe he giveth him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Cuſtom above that is due by Law. But the Statute of 27 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 26.
<note place="margin">27 E. 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 26.</note> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore cited doth make this point clear without ſcruple, which confirmeth the Charter of 31. <hi>E.</hi> 1. entirely, and by that the encreaſe of Cuſtom by three pence in the pound, which is by name mentioned in the Statute, is now due by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>If you will have the King hold this encreaſe of Cuſtom by Prerogative, you go directly againſt his meaning; for it appeareth by that which preſently fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170211:24"/>this Grant, that the King took this encreaſe of Cuſtom by way of contract onely, and not by way of Prerogative; for the ſame year following he directeth his Writs to the Officers of his Ports, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing the contract made with the Aliens by <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> adding further that ſome Denizens were willing to pay the like Cuſtom, upon the ſame Immunities to them to be granted, and doth aſſign his Officers to gather it, but with this clauſe, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Si gratanter &amp; abſque coertione ſolvere voluerint, ita quod aliquem Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorem de regno &amp; poteſtate noſtrâ ad praeſtationes &amp; cuſtumas hujuſmodi invito ſolvendas nullatenùs diſtringatis.</hi>
               </q> Nothing can more plainly expreſs, that the Kings intention was not to demand this by way of Prerogative, but by force of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. If there were ſuch a Prerogative in the Crown, as of right to have Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, how cometh it to paſs this Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative never yet had fruit or effect? for this I can maintain, That the King of <hi>England</hi> hath not one penny Cuſtom or Impoſition upon Merchandizes, elder then the fourth year of Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> that he holdeth not by Act of Parliament,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170211:24"/>and by the peoples grant: The eldeſt that he hath is that of Woolls, Wooll-fells and Leather, and that is by Act of Parliament, as appeareth in the Statute 25 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.
<note place="margin">25 E. 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> the Tonnage and Poundage by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the firſt year of every Kings reign.</p>
            <p>The Aliens encreaſe of Cuſtom by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament 27 <hi>E.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 26.
<note place="margin">27. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap</hi> 26.</note> Then this Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative hath been much neglected, that it was never called on to be put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, untill now of late years.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Statutes made for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining our Kings,
<note place="margin">Statute 3</note> from the exerciſe of this pretended Prerogative, which is the third matter I ſtand upon: Thoſe that have maintained the Kings Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative in this point, have endeavored to interpret thoſe Statutes, to extend onely to reſtrain him from impoſing upon Wooll, Wooll-fells, and Leather, which are ſtaple commodities: And the reaſon they give for this reſtraint more then for other goods, is becauſe the King, by Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, is reſtrained to a Cuſtom certain for thoſe commodities, as the half Mark a Sack of Wooll, and half a Mark three hundred Wooll-fells and thirteen ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170211:25"/>four pence a Laſt of Leather; and therefore great reaſon he ſhould not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed this Cuſtom in theſe Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>This Objection receiveth many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers: Firſt it appeareth both by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs letter of divers of the Laws made in this point, by the occaſion that induced the making of the Laws, and by the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of them, that all other Wares and Merchandiſes, as well as thoſe of the ſtaple, were within the purpoſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of thoſe Laws: Secondly The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alleadged why there ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint for the ſtaple Commodities, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then for the other, is miſtaken; for the Lords and Commons did grant to <hi>E.</hi> 1. by Act of Parliament the cuſtom of the half Mark for Wooll, Wooll-fels, and Leather, which was matter of meer grace and liberality, and includeth no reſtraint in it, but rather a favourable extention, quite contrary to the ſence of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; according to that rule of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, <hi>Gratioſa ampliari decet, odioſa reſtringi.</hi> And admit ſome Laws be made expreſly to reſtrain impoſitions upon Wooll, Wooll-fells, and Leather, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170211:25"/>that the occaſion of making ſuch Laws was the actual impoſing, upon thoſe goods at that time, ſhall we not by good conſtruction, <hi>Secundum mentem extenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vam legis,</hi> extend this Law to other Wares and Merchandizes that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame miſchief? If we look to the reaſon of the Law, we ſhall make no doubt of it; for that is becauſe the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions were without aſſent of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not becauſe they were upon ſuch, and ſuch Commodities. Beſides thoſe Laws ſo made are <hi>declarativae juris anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui, non introductivae novi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the enumeration of thoſe Statutes, which I conceive make directly to this purpoſe, I will endeavour rather to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Objections made againſt them, then to enforce the ſenſe and meaning of them, which is very plain and open, and needs no interpretation. The firſt Statute enforced is, <hi>Mag. Charta cap</hi> 30. made in the ninth year of <hi>H.</hi> 3. by which it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, that all Merchants ſhall have free egreſs and regreſs, out of, and into this Realm, with their goods and merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes, to buy, and ſell, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>ſine omnibus malis tolnetis per antiquas &amp; rectas
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170211:26"/>conſuetudines:</hi>
               </q> In which words we may infer, that both the uſe and right of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing are abſolutely excluded, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred; for <hi>Conſuetudo,</hi> which in this caſe is to be taken for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage,</hi> which is <hi>mos</hi> (not improperly for <hi>Portorium,</hi> a duty paid in money, as our Engliſh word Cuſtom, in one ſence doth ſignifie) implieth a beginning, and continuance by conſent, and will of the parties, not by power and enforcement, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a Cuſtom; and therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be an Impoſition: for that ariſeth meerly out of the will and power of their impoſer, and is againſt the will of him upon whoſe goods it is ſet: But take <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudo</hi> either for <hi>Mos</hi> or <hi>Portorium,</hi> the epithites with which it is qualified, <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum,</hi> and <hi>rectum,</hi> do deſcribe it to be of that nature, that it cannot be an Impoſition: for <hi>antiquum,</hi> in legal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, is that which is time out of mind, that is not an Impoſition: for then by continuance of time it ſhould grow a right by preſcription, and were juſtifiable: <hi>Rectum</hi> implieth a limited right, which inferreth there may be a wrong, and exceeding of that right which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170211:26"/>is not in impoſitions: for if there be a right in the King to impoſe, the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, time, and other circumſtances are in his diſcretion; the right is illimited: And if he ſet on never ſo great an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, there is as much right in it, as if it be never ſo ſmall: the exceſs maketh it a burthen, but not a wrong.</p>
            <p>We may further obſerve, that in the Statute, <hi>Malum tolnetum,</hi> which is evill Toll, is ſet down by way of antitheſis to <hi>antiqua,</hi> and <hi>recta conſuetudo;</hi> by which is inferred, that exactions upon Wares and Merchandizes, not qualified with theſe two properties of <hi>antiquum</hi> and <hi>rectum,</hi> are evill and unjuſt. This is made more evident by a Record in the Tower of the ſixteenth year of <hi>H.</hi> 3. which was a Mandat ſent by the King to the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of his Ports for the execution of this Law made in 9 <hi>H.</hi> 3. whereby it is commanded,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. clauſ</hi> 16. <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>num.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Quod emnibus Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus in portum ſuum venientibus cum vinis, &amp; aliis merchandizis, ſcire faciant, quod ſalvò &amp; ſecurè in terram Angliae veniant cum vinis &amp; merchandizis ſuis, faciendo inde rectas &amp; dubitas conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudines,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170211:27"/>nec ſibi timeant de malis tolnetis, quae iis faciat Rex, vel in terrâ ſuá fieri per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittat.</hi>
               </q> By this record the word <hi>Conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo</hi> is interpreted to be <hi>mos,</hi> not <hi>porto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium;</hi> otherwiſe it ſhould have been <hi>ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendo conſuetudines,</hi> not <hi>faciendo.</hi> Alſo theſe words <hi>entiquum &amp; rectum</hi> in the Statute in this Writ are <hi>rectum &amp; debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> which doth more enforce a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of right and duty, which by no means can be intended in impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Objections againſt this Law were made in the laſt Argument. Firſt, That it was made for Aliens: This is true; the words of the Law do plainly ſhew it was made for Aliens: But if the State was ſo careful to provide for them ſhall we not judge that with Denizens it was ſo already? And that this Statute was made to extend that liberty by Act of Parliament to Aliens, which Denizens had by the Common Law, ſucceeding times did ſo conceive of it, as appeareth by the Statute of 2.
<note place="margin">2. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. the words are, that all Merchants, Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Princes may go and come with their merchandizes in <hi>England</hi> after the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170211:27"/>tenor of the great Charter, and that Writs be thereupon ſent to all the Sheriffs in <hi>England,</hi> and to Mayors and Bayliffs of good Towns, where need ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Objection was made in the laſt Argument, out of theſe words of the Statute of <hi>M. Char.</hi> that Merchants might freely traffique, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>niſi publicè an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tea prohibiti fuerint:</hi>
               </q> by which was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, that the King had power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain and prohibit Traffique; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to impoſe. It is agreed, there may be a publick reſtraint of traffique upon reſpects of the common good of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; but whether that which is called <hi>publica prohibitio</hi> in the Statute, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the King alone, or by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, is a queſtion: For ſuch reſtraints have ſtill been by Parliament. But ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the King may make a reſtraint of traffique in part for ſome publick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Commonwealth, he doth this in point of protection, as truſted by the Commonwealth, to do that which is for the publick good of the Kingdom; but if he uſe this truſt to make a gain and benefit by impoſing,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170211:28"/>that is a breach of the truſt, and a ſale of government and protection. But more of this ſhall be hereafter ſpoken in the anſwering of the main Objections.</p>
            <p>The next Law is that notable Statute of <hi>E.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> in the 25 year of his reign, made upon the very point in queſtion; the words are theſe. And foraſmuch as the moſt part of the Commonalty of this Realm finde themſelves ſore grieved with the male toll of Woolls, that is, to wit, a toll of forty ſhillings for every ſack of Wooll, and have petitioned to us for to releaſe the ſame; We at their requeſt have clearly releaſed it, and have granted for us and our Heirs, that we ſhall not take ſuch things, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their common conſent and good will, ſaving to us and our Heirs the Cuſtoms of Woolls, Skins, and Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther granted before by the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Againſt the application of this Law, to the queſtion now in hand, many Objections were made; ſome out of matter precedent to the Law, ſome out of the Law it ſelf, ſome out of matter ſubſequent and following after
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170211:28"/>the Law: For matter precedent; It was objected out of <hi>Thomas Walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tho. Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham in E.</hi> 1. <hi>fo.</hi> 71, 72, 73. <hi>edit. per W. Camb. impreſ. Francof.</hi> 1603.</note> an Hiſtoriographer of good cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, that writ of that time when the Statute was made, That in the Petition of grievances given to King <hi>E.</hi> 1. by the people in the 25 year of his reign, upon which petition the Statute was made, that they found themſelves not grieved in point of right, but in point of exceſs; the words are, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Communitas ſentit ſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatam de vectigali lanarum, quod nimis eſt oneroſum.</hi> viz. <hi>de quolibet ſacco</hi> 40 <hi>s. &amp; de lanâ fractâ ſeptem marcas;</hi>
               </q> ſo they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the cauſe of their grief, that it was too heavy; which is to be applied to the point of exceſs, not of right.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that if the words had been <hi>(quia eſt nimis oneroſum)</hi> this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction might have been made out of them; becauſe the word <hi>(quia)</hi> had induced a declaration of the cauſe of that which was formerly affirmed: but the words are <hi>(quod nimis oneroſum)</hi> which doth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſitively affirm that the impoſition, <hi>de facto,</hi> was intolerable for the greatneſs of it, which doth not therefore admit that it is tolerable, in reſpect of the right the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170211:29"/>King had to impoſe. But this is made clear by the general word precedent in the preamble of the Petition which doth evidently infer, they grounded their complaint upon point of right, not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on point of exceſs; the words are theſe, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Tota terrae communitas ſentit ſe valdè gravatam, quia non tractantur ſecundum leges &amp; conſuetudines terrae, ſecundum quas tractari anteceſſores ſui ſolebant ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, ſed voluntariè excluduntur.</hi>
               </q> After which preamble, among the particulars, this of forty ſhillings upon a ſack of Wooll is ranked, but with a dependency of that expreſſed in the preamble for the point of right. But ſeeing we light upon Hiſtory, which though it be of ſmall authority in a Law argument yet being the Hiſtory of our own Realm, hath fit and proper uſe in the common counſel of the Realm,
<note place="margin">Matth Weſtm. fo. 430. Edit. per H. Savile mil. Franco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furti 1601.</note> I will purſue it a little further. Out of <hi>Matth. Weſtm.</hi> a Writer that lived much nearer the time of the Law made, then <hi>Thomas Walſingham,</hi> he ſaith, That the Commons by their petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons required, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Ne Rex de caetero tallagia uſurparet, &amp; voluntarias ſuper his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductas exactiones de caetero quaſi in irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170211:29"/>revocaret;</hi>
               </q> by which it appeareth, that the point of the complaint was, that the exactions laid on them were volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, that is, at the Kings will, without aſſent of Parliament. Out of the Law it, ſelf it hath much been preſſed, as firſt the Commons made petition to the King, whereupon they infer out of the nature of the word (petition) that their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding was by way of grievance, for the exceſs and inconvenience, as a matter of grace, not in courſe of juſtice for the wrong</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, That conſidering the quality of the parties to this action, it being between the King and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, duty and good manners doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce gentleneſs and humility of terms, without blemiſh or diminution of the force of right. It is according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor of <hi>Job,</hi> cap. 9. v. 15.
<note place="margin">Job 9.15</note> 
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Though I were juſt, yet would I not anſwer, but I would make ſupplication to my Judge.</hi>
               </q> But in our forms of Law, be the right of the Subject never ſo clear, manifeſt, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all; yet if his own be detained from him by the King, he hath no other Writ or Action to recover, but
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170211:30"/>a meer petition, <hi>Supplicat Colſitudini, &amp;c.</hi> So as if the word Petition to the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer defect of right in the Petitioner, there can be no caſe where the King can do the Subject wrong.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Objection out of the body of the Law is that the King doth releaſe that impoſition of forty ſhillings, which implieth a right ſetled in him. But to this I anſwer, That it is no neceſſary infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whereſoever a releaſe of right is: for it is uſed for claim onely, or where poſſeſſion was, though wrongful, and that <hi>in majorem ſecuritatem, quia a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundans cautela non nocet;</hi> but in this caſe, a Releaſe was very expedient, and for ſome reſpect neceſſary, to extinguiſh a right the King had in this impoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Merchants themſelves: For this impoſition, though it were not ſet on by aſſent of Parliament, yet was it not ſet on by the Kings abſolute power; but was granted to him by the Merchants themſelves who were to be charged with it: ſo the grievance was the violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the right of the people, in ſetting it on without their aſſent in Parliament, not the damage that grew by it; for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170211:30"/>that did onely touch the Merchants, who could not juſtly complain thereof, becauſe it was their own act and grant. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by two notable Records,
<note place="margin">22. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>Origen. in Scac. Rem. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> the one 22. <hi>E.</hi> 1. A Writ to the Treaſurer and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the Exchequer in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to diſcharge the Merchants there of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions on Woolls; in which the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeth, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Licet in ſubſiaium Guerrae Regis pro recuperandâ terrâ Vaſconià, mercato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res gratanter conceſſerunt per biennium vel triennium, ſi tantum duravit Guerra, de ſacco lanae, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 26. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>mem. Scac. Rem. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> The other Record is the Writ of publication, that in 26. <hi>E.</hi> 1. went out after the Statute of 25. in which Writ the King reciteth thus, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Cum nos ad inſtantiam Communitaetis Regni noſtri re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerimus cuſtumam</hi> 40 <hi>s. nobis nuper in ſubſidium Guerrae noctrae contrae Regem Franciae conceſſum &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> A third Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made out of the body of the Statute, by thoſe which have argued on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary part, was upon theſe words, that the King would take (no ſuch things) without common conſent; by which words they conceived the intention of the Law was limited preciſely to impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſet upon Wooll, and not on other
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170211:31"/>commodities, which are not ſuch things, but other: and for this they alledge this reaſon, That it was not probable when the complaint was only for an impoſition on Wooll, that the King would give a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for other things not ſpoken of, for which there was no cauſe of complaint.</p>
            <p>To this a full anſwer is given many ways: Firſt, out of the <hi>(Saving)</hi> in the Act, which extends to other things then to Wooll, as to Wooll-fells and Leather; therefore the purview of the Act by theſe words (ſuch things) extendeth to more then the Wooll; for there needs no <hi>ſaving,</hi> but for that which is contained in the purview. Secondly, The reaſon alledged, that no more by likelihood ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medied but for Wooll, becauſe onely that was complained of, is falſe: For the complaint of the Commons was not onely for this impoſition on Wooll, but divers other burthens and grievances of the like nature. And this will appear if we compare all the parts of the Law, the one with the other: For this Law is in the form of a Charter written in French, and beginneth, <hi>Edward by the Grace of God, &amp;c.</hi> and is an entire grant,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170211:31"/>and Inſtrument without Fractions, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and Chapters, as it is now print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and containeth in it, next before this laſt clauſe concerning the impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on Woolls, which in the printed Book is <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. That the King, for no bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, from thenceforth, will take no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of aids, miſes, nor priſes, but by common aſſent. This word <hi>(miſes)</hi> in French ſignifieth properly impoſitions, derived of the word <hi>mitto,</hi> in Latine <hi>(to put)</hi> ſo the word <hi>(ſuch things)</hi> is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion to all the premiſes, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation not onely to that which is made, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. by the Printer, and concerneth the male toll of Woolls; but to that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent which is (all other aids) impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and takings.</p>
            <p>The Writ of publication of this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute ſent out to all parts in 26. <hi>E.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">Mem. Scac. in 26. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>Rem. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth plain this conſtruction; the words of it are, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Concedentes quod cuſtumam il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam vel aliam, ſine voluntate vel com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni aſſenſu non capiamus:</hi>
               </q> Theſe words <hi>(vel aliam)</hi> are indefinite, and extend to any other whatſoever, beſides that of Woolls. The Writ doth further diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge Merchants for the commodities of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170211:32"/>Wooll-fells, and Leather, which are not complained of by name in the Statute; and therefore the Law was intended to other impoſitions as well as to thoſe upon Woolls.</p>
            <p>The Objection made out of matter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent to the Statute was this, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this Law of 25 <hi>E.</hi> 1. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions that before the Statute had been ſet on other Merchandize then Woolls, were ſtill anſwered after the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute; and for inſtance of this, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged,
<note place="margin">16. E. 1. <hi>Orig. R. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> that whereas 16. <hi>E.</hi> 1. an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of 40 <hi>s.</hi> the Tun was ſet upon Wines brought into the Kingdom, an accompt was made of this in the Exchequer in 26. <hi>E.</hi> 1. as by the Records there appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; by which it ſeemeth that the Law of 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1 was not taken to extend to Wines, and ſuch other Commodities, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Woolls named in the Statute. It is true, ſuch an impoſition was ſet on by <hi>E.</hi> 1. in the ſixteenth year of his reign,
<note place="margin">25, <hi>&amp;</hi> 26 E. 1. <hi>de compt. T. Mich. R. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> and an accompt made for it 25. and 26. But it appeareth by the Record of the accompt, that it was made for the time ended before the Statute made: As from the eighteenth of <hi>May,</hi> 16.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170211:32"/>
               <hi>E</hi> 1. to 23 <hi>Jul.</hi> 22. <hi>E.</hi> 1. But there is no Record, that ever any accompt was made for any money received for that impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the time after the Statute made; neither was it very willingly anſwered before; for it appeareth by the Record that it was ten years after the ſetting of it.</p>
            <p>The third Statute alledged on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Subject is that 34. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">34. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> the words are theſe, No tallage or aid ſhall be taken or levied by us, or our heirs in our Realm, without the good will and aſſent of our Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Earls, Barons, Knights, Burgeſſes, and other freemen of the Land. Againſt this was objected, That this Statute was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended onely upon the Taxes and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of things; The word <hi>Auxilium</hi> makes it clear, that it is to be intended further then of things within the Realm; for <hi>Tallagium</hi> is commonly intended of Domeſtical Taxes, but <hi>Auxilium</hi> is the moſt uſual term for impoſitions upon goods imported and exported, as by the Acts of Parliament by which ſuch impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions are given to the King in which they are called moſt commonly by the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170211:33"/>name of Aids, as proceeding of good will and benevolence.</p>
            <p>The fourth Statute alledged on this part is that of 5.
<note place="margin">5. E. 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Rot. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 14. juſt in point of the matter in queſtion; and therefore I will ſet it down as I finde it <hi>Verbatim</hi> in the Record in the Tower, <q xml:lang="frm">
                  <hi>Enſement novelles cuſtomes ſont levies, &amp; antients enhaunces come ſur levies drapes, vine, aver du pois, &amp; aut choſes purquoy les Merchantes veynont pluis vilement, &amp; meynes de bien, menynont en la terre, &amp; les Merchants eſtrangers demurront pluis longment que ils ſoleyent faier, pur le quel demoure le choſes ſont le pluis enhaunces que ils ne ſoloyent eſtre, al dammage de roy, &amp; de ſon people. Nous ordonomus que tout manners de male tolls levies puies de Coronement de Roy Ed. faier de Roy Henry ſoyent entirement ouſtes, &amp; de tout eſtreints put tout jours, nient contriſteant le Chartre que le dict Roy Ed fiſt us Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants aliens, pur ceo que il fuit fair con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra le grand. Char. &amp; encountre le Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe de la City de Londres, &amp; ſans aſſent de Baronage, &amp;c. Savant neque dont al Roy le cuſtome de leynes, peulx, &amp; de quirs, &amp;c. ſi aver les doet.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170211:33"/>
            <p>By this Law is recited. That by the levying of new Cuſtoms, and by the raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of old, Traffique was deſtroyed, and all things made dear; And therefore all new Impoſitions and Cuſtoms were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged <hi>Chartâ Mercatoriâ,</hi> by which Cuſtom that was encreaſed on Aliens, was taken away, and the reaſon alledged; Becauſe it was <hi>ſans aſſent de Baronage,</hi> and againſt the great Charter. And this is further with this clauſe, Saving to the King his Cuſtom of Wooll, Wooll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fells and Leather, <hi>Si aver les doet.</hi> Great wars have been raiſed againſt the credit of this Law in the Parliament Houſe and Three things have been eſpecially object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt it:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it is no Law; for it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced upon the King, by ſome of the Nobility that were too ſtrong for him, the Realm being then in tumult and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny about the quarrel of <hi>Peirce</hi> of <hi>Gave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> ſo never had the Kings free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; but he gave way unto it for fear of greater miſcheif.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That in it ſelf it is unjuſt, as in taking away the Cuſtom granted to the King by <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> 31.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170211:34"/>
               <hi>E.</hi> 1. and in making doubt whether the King ſhould have the Cuſtom of Woolls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by thoſe words, <hi>Saving it to him, Si aver les doet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Objection is, That if it were a Law, it is repealed.</p>
            <p>To theſe I give particular Anſwers.</p>
            <p>To the firſt: That this Statute was made both at the inſtance of the King and people, with a purpoſe and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on all parts to ſettle things in a ſtay and order, both in the Kings houſe and Commonwealth; the King and his Nobles ſtanding in good terms, when this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was taken in hand; and it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun and ended with great ſolemnity and ceremony: For the King in the third year of his reign gave Commiſſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Great Seal to 32.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Com.</hi> 16. <hi>Mar.</hi> 3. <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>Rot. ordin.</hi> 5. E. 2.</note> Lords ſpiritual and temporal; of which there were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven Biſhops eight Earls and thirteen Barons; they being as Committees of the higher Houſe to deviſe Ordinances for the good government of his houſe and his Realm. In which Commiſſion he doth for the honor of God, the good of him,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170211:34"/>and of his Realm, of his freewill grant to the Prelates, Earls, and Barons, and others elected by the whole Kingdom, full power to ordain the State of his houſe and Realm by ſuch Ordinances as by them ſhould be made, to the honor of God, the honor and profit of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church, the honor of himſelf, the profit of him and his people, according to right and reaſon, and the oath he made at his Coronation.</p>
            <p>Theſe joyning with others of diſcreet Commons in Parliament, and taking e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of them a ſolemn oath for their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere demeanor in the buſineſs, did make this and other Ordinances, which were ſo well liked of by the King, that after they were made, he took an oath to obſerve them, and cauſed them to be publiſhed in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard by the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> by denouncing Excommunication againſt all that ſhould wilfully infringe them:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pullic.</hi> 3. <hi>Kal. Oct.</hi> 5. E. 2. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. ord. Pat.</hi> 5. <hi>Oct.</hi> 5. E. 2. <hi>Rot. ordin.</hi>
               </note> And by his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents dated 5. <hi>Oct</hi> 5. <hi>regni ſui,</hi> did ſend them through the Realm to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and from thenceforth to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, thereby ſignifying his great liking and approbation of them; after which
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170211:35"/>they had the force and power of Laws given unto them in the Parliament, in the fifth year of his reign.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Objection, which is the injuſtneſs of the Law, inſtanced in two points; The taking away of <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> and the doubting of the Kings right to the Cuſtom of Wooll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fells, and Leather, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To the firſt of theſe, I deny it to be unjuſt, but to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of <hi>England,</hi> and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Kingdom: for that Charter did contain in it divers grants of things which were not in the power of the King to grant without aſſent of Parliament; the trial <hi>per medietatem linguae,</hi> and other things tending to the alteration of the Law, and burdening of the people; and therefore that Charter never had his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted and ſetled force, until it was confirmed by Act of Parliament, but lay aſleep almoſt twenty years together, without being put in execution, between 5, <hi>E.</hi> 2. and 27. <hi>E.</hi> 3. when it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; for the doubt that is ſuppoſed to be made in the Statute of the Kings right to the Cuſtom of Wooll, Wooll-fells and Leather, I take it, there is no ſuch doubt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170211:35"/>made: For the words <hi>(Saving the Kings right to the Cuſtom of Woolls, ſi aver les dort)</hi> have this conſtruction, that is, at ſuch times as he ought to have it: ſo the word <hi>(ſi)</hi> hath the ſignification of <hi>(quando)</hi> for it had been a folly to have made a Saving of that, of the right where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they had doubted, neither is it likely but that they would have taken it away, if it had not been lawful; but there was no colour to doubt of the right of it, for it was given by Act of Parliament, and ever continued in force without chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge or exceptions to the lawfulneſs of it.</p>
            <p>The third Objection is, That this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute is repealed: To this I plead, <hi>Nullum valet recordum.</hi> If it be repealed, it muſt be by Act of Parliament, for <hi>unum quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que diſſolvitur iiſdem modis quibus eſt col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatum:</hi> I and others have ſearched the Records of the Realm, and endervoured by all means to inform our ſelves of the truth herein, &amp; we can find no Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of repeal: The truth is, ſome Kings finding theſe Laws not to ſort to their wills and humors have endeavoured to ſuppreſs them, but they did never yet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170211:36"/>a repeal of them by Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>But it is further urged, That although there were no formal repeal of the Law, yet it was never put in execution as a Law, but even preſently upon the making was rejected, and uſe and practiſe went quite againſt it: and for inſtance hereof, a Record was vouched that <hi>E.</hi> 2 held himſelf ſo little bound by it, as that in the 11. year of his reign he ſet an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition without aſſent of Parliament up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Wooll, Wooll-fells, Leather, Wines, Cloth, <hi>Aver de pois,</hi> and divers other kind of Merchandizes. To this I anſwer, that if it were true, that a diſtinct and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent King, as he was, did contrary to the Law, doth this make the Law void, and no Law? But if we look into the whole Record, and ſcan this action of <hi>E.</hi> 2. from the beginning of it unto the end, we ſhall finde it a very good inſtance to prove the practice and execution both of this Law of 5. <hi>E.</hi> 2: and of that in 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. for it is true that <hi>E.</hi> 2. in the eleventh year of his reign did borrow of the Merchants a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſum of money above the due Cuſtom of Woolls, Wooll-fells, Wine, <hi>Averdepois,</hi> Leather, and ſuch other goods imported
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170211:36"/>and exported; but it appeareth by the Record, he took it but for one year; he took it by the advice and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Merchants, and he took it <hi>per viam mutui,</hi> as a loan.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. clauſ.</hi> 11. E. 2.</note> The direction of the Writ is, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Collectoribus mutui nobis per mercatores alienigenas &amp; indigenas de cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis rebus &amp; Merchandiſis uſque ad certum tempus faciendi.</hi>
               </q> This was done in good terms, he did not claim it as his right, but did borrow it, which I do think is a good evidence againſt his right: But what became of this? the State would not abide it, for all theſe fair ſhews. And therefore afterwards the King ſendeth out other Writs by which he diſchargeth all Merchandizes of this Loan, ſaving on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wooll, Wooll-fells, and Leather; and for the Loan taken upon thoſe Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, it was limited to continne but until <hi>Michaelmas</hi> after, and good ſecurity was given to the Merchants by the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers to pay themſelves by way of defal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation out of the Cuſtoms which ſhould be due after <hi>Machaelmas,</hi> thoſe ſums which were ſo borrowed of them.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium</hi> 11. E. 2.</note> The words of the Record are worth the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Cum pro expeditione guerra Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170211:37"/>&amp; aliis arduis &amp; urgentibus neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus nobis multipliciter incumbentibus, pro quarum exoneratione quaſi infinitam pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniam refundere oporobit, pecunia pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum indigeamus in praeſenti, &amp; nuper pro eo quod exitus regni &amp; terrarum noſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſimul cum pecunia nobis in ſubven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione praemiſſorum tam per Clerum quam Communitatem regni noſtri conceſſa ad ſumptus praedictos cum feſtinatione qua ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediret faciendos, non ſufficiunt, exquiren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vias &amp; modos quibus poſſemus pecuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am habere commodius &amp; decentius pro prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſis, de conſilio &amp; aaviſamento quorun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam mercatorum tam alienigenarum quam indigenarum viam invenimus infra ſcript. viz.</hi>
               </q> And ſo ſetteth down the manner of the loan, and the ſecurity for the payment of it: This (I take it) was neither an Impoſition nor a wrong in any reſpect. Alſo by the firſt Record it appeareth, that the Loan ſet on Wines, <hi>Averdepois,</hi> and ſuch other Commodities, beſides Wooll, Woll-fells and Leather, were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſcharged by <hi>E.</hi> 2. which ſheweth they were taken to be within the intent of the Statute of 25 <hi>E.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>The fifth Statute alledged on the behalf
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170211:37"/>of the Subject is that 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Stat</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 21.
<note place="margin">14. E. 3. <hi>Stat.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.</note> by which the Commons pray the King to take no more then the old Cuſtom of the half Mark. The King prayeth aid of the Commons for a time above the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom upon his neceſſity of Wars. And the concluſion is, that by that Act the King doth grant that after the Feaſt of Pentecoſt, twelve moneths following, he will take no more of Woolls, Wooll-fells and Leather, but the old Cuſtom, and doth promiſe to charge, ſet, or aſſeſs upon the Cuſtom but in manner as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>The ſixth Statute is 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Stat</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">14. E. 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1</note> 
               <hi>cap.</hi> 1. The King doth grant by way of Charter to the Prelats, Earls, Barons, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Citizens, Burgeſſes and Merchants, that they be not from henceforth charged nor grieved to make any aid or ſuſtain charge, if it be not by the common conſent of the Prelates, Earls, Barons, and other great men, and Commons of the Realm, and that in Parliament.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Statutes grew upon an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an Impoſition ſet on Wooll by the King without aſſent of Parliament: Little hath been objected againſt them, but only to the firſt, that it was obtained of grace,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170211:38"/>and not upon inſtance of right, which they gather out of the words of the Law, which are, The Commons pray the King that he would ſtabliſh, that from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth no more then the old Cuſtom be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. The like reaſon may be made againſt the King out of the ſame words in the ſame Law: for the King in the ſame Act prayeth the Commons to give him an Impoſition upon Woolls for a time above the old Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom: but the Record of the Petitions ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited in Parliament on which theſe two Laws are made, cleareth the objection.</p>
            <p>The firſt was delivered by the Lords in this form,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Par.</hi> 13. E. 3. <hi>num.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Les grands volunt,</hi> that the male toll ſet on Woolls newly, be altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, and that the old Cuſtom be held, and that they may have this in point of Charter, and by inrolment in Parliament. This word <hi>(volunt)</hi> had been too high for a fuit of grace, and therefore muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended of right. The Commons Petition in form is ſomewhat humble, but in effect and purpoſe is rough and ſtern: The words are theſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Par.</hi> 13. E. 3. <hi>num.</hi> 13.</note> The Commons pray that the male toll of Woolls be taken as it was uſed in antient time, which is now enhanced without the aſſent of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170211:38"/>and <hi>(grandes)</hi> as we conceive, and that if it be otherwiſe demanded, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of the Commons may arreſt them without being challenged. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to theſe Petitions, the firſt of theſe two Laws is by inrolment in Parliament: the ſecond is in form of a Charter; the firſt doth expreſs ſome ſpecial commodities: The ſecond doth reach generally at all.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh Law directly touching this point, is that 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Stat.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">13. E. 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2</note> The King doth grant according to the Great Charter, that all Merchants, Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens and foreigners may without let ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come into the Realm of <hi>England</hi> with their goods and Merchandizes, and ſafely tarry, and ſafely return, paying the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, Cuſtoms and other profits reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably due. Upon the words of this Law, was great advantage taken, in this, that beſides Cuſtom and Subſidy, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all the certain and ordinary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties the King hath upon the wares and goods of Merchants, there are other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits ſpoken of to be due: Theſe they affirm cannot be underſtood but of Impoſitions by the King without aſſent of Parliament.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer; if they were not du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170211:39"/>due to the King beſides Cuſtom and Subſidy, which might ſatisfie the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe words, this objection might have had ſome colour in it; but it is plain that beſides theſe two, there are other profits due to the King upon Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants goods, as Scavage, Tonage, and the like.</p>
            <p>And you ſhall finde a Petition in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Par.</hi> 50. E. 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 163.</note> 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. againſt the raiſing of theſe above the old rate.</p>
            <p>The eighth Law is,
<note place="margin">15. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Stat.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. whereby it is enacted that every Merch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant may freely buy and ſell, and paſs the Sea with their Merchandizes of Wooll and all other things, paying the Cuſtom of old time uſed, according to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made in the laſt Parliament in Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, which was the <hi>Stat.</hi> 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. This Law doth expreſly exclude the novelty of Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>The ninth Law is that 18.
<note place="margin">18 E. 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 3. whereby it is enacted, That the Sea be open to all manner of Merchants to paſs with their Merchandizes where it ſhall pleaſe them.</p>
            <p>The tenth is,
<note place="margin">27. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2</note> 27. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2, <hi>cap.</hi> 2 for the aſſurance of Merchants-ſtrangers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170211:39"/>the King doth will and grant for him and his Heirs, that nothing ſhall be taken over the due Cuſtoms, not taken of them to his uſe by colour of ſuit, or in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner againſt their wills.</p>
            <p>The eleventh is, 38. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">38. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> that all manner of Merchants aliens and Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens may buy and ſell all manner of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes, and freely carry them out of the Realm, paying the Cuſtoms and Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies thereof due.</p>
            <p>The laſt is 22. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.
<note place="margin">22. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> by which it was enacted that Tables ſhould be ſet up in Ports, by which the certainty and very duty of every Cuſtom, Toll, and Duty, or ſum of money to be demanded and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Wares and Merchandizes ſhall and may plainly appear and be declared, to the intent that nothing be exacted other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then in old time hath been uſed and accuſtomed.</p>
            <p>By this late Law it appeareth that the judgment of the whole Parliament was at that time, That nothing was due upon Wares and Merchandizes, but that which which was certain: and had been antiently due, by which Impoſitions are excluded, whoſe qualities are novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170211:40"/>and incertainty, as being ſet on, as preſent occaſion moveth, and proportioned for quantity and other circumſtances, as the will of the King di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Laws which I conceive moſt directly tend to the reſtraining the Kings of <hi>England</hi> from the exerciſe of that irregular power of impoſing, at the firſt offered by them to be put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet not preſſed as their right, and never practiſed but upon oppoſition of the whole State, and at laſt deſerted and given over until of late; as by that which followeth in the fourth place will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
            <p>My fourth and laſt aſſertion is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cuſtom</hi> 4</note> That this practiſe of impoſing without aſſent of Parliament, is <hi>contra morem Majorum.</hi> In this I will make an hiſtorical perluſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the times paſt, whereby I will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover and make known what paſſages have been in this buſineſs in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and eſpecially in the high Court of Parliament for the ſpace of 300 years and more laſt paſt, ſince the beginning of the reign of <hi>E.</hi> 1 ſithence which time, and not before, this Kingdom hath grown into
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170211:40"/>the glory and reputation of foraigne traffique. And as a worthy Gentleman of the Kings learned Councel, made cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine conſiderations upon this queſtion, framed and ſtrengthened out of the greatneſs of his wit and reaſon: ſo I grounding my ſelf upon the practice of former times, which is the ſafeſt rule whereby to ſquare the right both of King and people in this Common-wealth, where their right is <hi>jus conſuetudinarium,</hi> a right that groweth by uſe and practice, I will propoſe unto you certaine obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations out of the action and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of former times untill the raignes of the two late Queenes: by which you may the better ground and frame your judgements in the determination of the right in this queſtion.</p>
            <p>My firſt obſervation is in point of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, that there never was any Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition ſet, but in time of actuall war, and <hi>duplicatis vexillis:</hi> they were ſet on very rarely and ſparingly, but for a ſhort time, and that certaine and definite, and upon ſome few commodities, and that by the aſſent of the Merchants that were to beare the burthen. In our
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170211:41"/>time the occaſion not ſo ſenſible, the continuance to be perpetual, the number many hundreds, almoſt no kinde of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity ſpared. I will give you ſome few Inſtances of theſe circumſtances out of the Records themſelves.</p>
            <p>The maletole of Wooll ſet on by King <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">22. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>orig. Scacc. Rent. Theſ.</hi> 22. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>mem. Scac. R. Theſ. T. Mich. Rot. parl.</hi> 17. <hi>E.</hi> 3.. <hi>nu</hi> 28.</note> 1. which gave the occaſion, of the Stat. 25. yeare of his raigne, was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by Merchants. The Record ſaith, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Mercatores gratanter conceſſerunt in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidium guerrae Regis.</hi>
               </q> It further ſheweth, it was for his neceſſity of Warre, which then was great alſo.</p>
            <p>For the time of <hi>F.</hi> 3. there need not many inſtances; for his whole raigne was almoſt an actuall warfare; As in the ſixt year of his raigne for his war in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> In the thirteenth year of his raigne for his war in <hi>France,</hi> ſeverall Impoſitions were ſet on</p>
            <p>In the ſeventeenth year of <hi>E.</hi> 3. the Record in the Tower mentioneth that forty ſhillings Impoſition was upon a ſacke of Wooll by the grant of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 38.</note> and it was in the time of VVar.</p>
            <p>In the twentieth yeare of King <hi>E.</hi> 3. it appeareth in the Record, that the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170211:41"/>then put upon VVools, was by the aſſent of Merchants for two years, for the neceſſity the King had in his paſſage over the ſea, to recover his right, and to defend the Realme.</p>
            <p>My ſecond obſervation is, Never any Impoſition was ſet on by the King out of Parliament, but complaint was made of it in Parliament; and not one that ever ſtood after ſuch complaint made, but remedy was afforded for it; <hi>Et quod Rex inconſulto fecit, conſulto revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavit,</hi> his Soveraigne power controlled his ſubordinate. In which it is a thing very notable, that the King in no one Caſe ever claimed, or ſo much as ever named his right or prerogative, which no doubt would have been done, if it had been thought due, but gave ſatisfaction to the complaint by one of theſe three waies; Either by diſcharging them quite, and making ſome good Law againſt them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by intreating the people to hold them ſome ſhort time by their favor.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by waving his preſent poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and taking that of their gift by Act
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170211:42"/>of Parliament, as an aide which he had ſet on by his abſolute power as an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <p>Inſtances of the firſt 25.
<note place="margin">25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 7. <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 38. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 26. 38. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. 45. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. 18. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10, 11. <hi>R.</hi> 18. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 1 21. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 11. <hi>R. Parl.</hi> 25. E. 3. <hi>n.</hi> 22. <hi>rot. Parl.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>E,</hi> 1. the Impoſitions of Wools taken off, and a Law made againſt it, and the King un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook for him and his ſucceſſors to doe ſo no more: 38 <hi>E.</hi> 3.26. the Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of three ſhillings foure pence on a ſacke of Wooll put off upon complaint, and a Law made againſt it, 38 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 2. the like Statute 45 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. upon a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of an Impoſition on Wools made in Parliament, 45. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 42. <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inſtances of the ſecond 21. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 11. a petition upon an Impoſition of 2. s. upon a ſacke of Wool, 2. s upon a tunne of VVine, and ſix pence upon <hi>aver de pois,</hi> all diſcharged preſently, ſaving the two ſhillings upon a ſacke of Wool, and for that intreated that it might ſtay till Eaſter following, and ſo it did, and was then taken away.</p>
            <p>Inſtance of the third 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 22. the Commons made petition againſt an impoſition of fourty ſhillings upon a ſack of Wool granted to the King by the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, ſhewing that they ought not to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170211:42"/>be bound by their act. The King did not claime right or juſtice, but becauſe his warres were great, upon his requeſt had it granted unto him for two yeeres by Act of Parliament, and pretended no title of Prerogative, neither was it ever ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>My third obſervation is that our Kings have acknowledged that it is not their right. <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orig. in Scau.</hi> 31. E. 1. <hi>R. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> 1 in his Writs he ſent to the Officers of his parts to levie three pence on the pound over the old cuſtome, or the Denizons as well as of the Aliens, and to ſuffer the Denizons to enjoy thoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges the Aliens did enjoy by the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the encreaſe of Cuſtome, doth give this direction expreſly. That they ſhould not take it of Denizons againſt their will. The words of the Record ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it very fully, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Cum mercatores extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nei &amp; alienigenae pro quibuſdam liberta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus eis per nos conceſſis &amp; priſcis noſtris quibuſcunque remiſſis, nobis de bonis &amp; merchandiſis ſuis quibuſcunque infra reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; poteſtatem noſtram adducend. ultra antiquas cuſtumas dare conceſſerint prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtationes &amp; cuſtumas ſubſcriptas, viz</hi>
               </q> and ſo ſetteth down the increaſes, and amongſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170211:43"/>the reſt this three pence upon the pound, and ſo proceedeth, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Ac quidam mercato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res de regno noſtro &amp; poteſtate noſtra, ut ipſis dictis libertatibus &amp; immunitatibus uti &amp; gaudere, &amp; quod de priſis noſtris quieti eſſe poſſiut, praeſtationes &amp; cuſtumas hujuſmodi de bonis &amp; merchandiſis ſuis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ſolvere velint, ut accepimus, aſſignavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus vos, &amp;c. ad cuſtumas &amp; praeſtationis praedictas de mercatoribus de regno &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate nostra colligend. qui eas gratanter &amp; ſine coercione ſolvere voluerint. Ita tamen quod aliquem mercatorem de dicto regno &amp; poteſtate noſtra ad praestationes &amp; cuſtumas hujuſmodi nobis invito ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vend. nallatenus diſtringatis.</hi>
               </q> Surely if <hi>E.</hi> 1. had claimed the prerogative of impoſing, he would never have given theſe cautions in the requiring of that which he had taken to be his due, as that they ſhould not exact it of any of his ſubjects that were not willing to pay it, nor trouble nor diſtraine them for it.</p>
            <p>In the twelfth yeere of <hi>E.</hi> 3. we finde the Record of certaine letters written from the King being then at <hi>Barwick</hi> in the Scottiſh Warres,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Alem.</hi> 12. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>dorm.</hi> 21. <hi>in turr<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </note> unto the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> in which letters
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170211:43"/>the King ſeemeth to have a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the devotion of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, and therefore earneſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth him to further his enterpriſes with his prayers to God, and then addeth further;</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <hi>Ad hoc pater, cum populus regni noſtri variis oneribus, tallagiis &amp; impoſitionibus hactenus praegravetur (quod dolenter referimus) ſed inevitabili neceſſitate compulſi de eiſdem oneribus ipſum adhuc relevare non valemus dictum populum, ut tautam neceſſitatem noſtram humiliter &amp; benigne patiatur &amp; caritativè ſuſtineat, &amp; priorem (quam penes nos concepit de cetero inſtanter in orationibus &amp; eleemoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſuis, oneribus praedicts, quae non ex malitia vel preſumptione voluntaria ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum gravant, non obſtantibus) exhibeant caritatem, indulgentiam muneribus &amp; aliis modis, quibus ſecundum Deum vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitis piis exhortationibus inducatis, &amp; nos penes eundem excuſetis; ſperamus namque per Dei gratiam, cujus manus cunctis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digentibus ſola ſufficiens, &amp; largiflua com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatur, beneficiis compenſatius dictum populum viſitare &amp; conſolari pro loco &amp; tempore opportunit.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:170211:44"/>
            <p>The principall thing I note out of this Record upon the very point of this my third obſervation, is that the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to excuſe himſelf of the burthens by him laid on the people, and to avoid the blemiſh of wrong and injuſtice in laying thereon, ſaith they were not <hi>onera ex preſumptione voluntaria,</hi> that is, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens that he preſumed to lay on at his owne will, whereby he condemneth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions without aſſent of Paliament, which are <hi>(onera ex voluntate Regis)</hi> to proceed of preſumption, which doth clearly exclude clame of right, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth the lawfulneſs of the Act. But there are divers other notable paſſages in the Record worthy our marking; As out of the word <hi>(praegravantur)</hi> uſed by the King wee may gather hee did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt theſe Impoſitions a grievous bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to his people, which ſheweth his owne pity of them. He ſaith further, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes referimus,</hi> ſhewing his griefe and remorſe at it, <hi>&amp; inevitabili neceſſitate compnlſi,</hi> he did it conſtrained by una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable neceſſity, ſhewing he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to it againſt his will, by that which violateth and breaketh all law which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170211:44"/>inferreth, he would not maintaine his action by law; <hi>Adhuc relevare non va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemus;</hi> this inſinuates, he would eaſe them in good time; <hi>caritatem exhibereut,</hi> they ſhould afford him charity in the bearing of them, as if ſo be in point of juſtice or right they need not, <hi>Penes eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem excuſetis,</hi> the Biſhop ſhould excuſe him to the people. By this he did clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leave the point of juſtification and ſo of right: laſtly he promiſeth he would viſit and comfort them <hi>beneficiis compenſativis,</hi> would give them recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for thoſe ſummes he had ſo raiſed of them; which ſheweth that he claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them not as due, for then he needed not give recompence for them.</p>
            <p>In the one and twentieth yeere of <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Parl</hi> 21. E. 3. <hi>n.</hi> 16.</note> 3. a petition was exhibited in Parliament, that Levies be not made by Commiſſion (ſo they be in this caſe) nor other things laid upon the people unleſs they be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Parliament. The Kings anſwer is, If any ſuch impoſitions were made, it was by great neceſſity, and with aſſent of the Prelates, Barons and ſome of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons preſent; yet he will not that ſuch Impoſitions not duly made be drawne
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170211:45"/>in conſequence. Here the King acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth an Impoſition not to be duly made, though with the conſent of the Higher Houſe, and ſome of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, becauſe it was not in full Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: much rather he would have thought ſo, if it had been by the King alone.</p>
            <p>King <hi>E.</hi> 4. (that was a rough and warlike Prince, and was more beholding to his ſword in the recovery of his right to the Crowne then to the affection of the people) at a Parliament held the ſeventh yeere of his reigne made a Speech to the Commons, Sir <hi>John Say</hi> being then Speaker, in which Speech is contained very notable matter, and very pertinent to our purpoſe; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Record is not in print, I will ſet downe the Kings Speech <hi>verbatim</hi> as it is entred upon the Parliament roll,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 7. <hi>E.</hi> 4. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quod die vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> 3. <hi>die Parl.</hi>
               </note> and then I will make a paraphraſe upon it; <q>
                  <hi>Iohn Say,</hi> and ye Sirs come to this my Court of Parliament for the Commons of this my Realme; The cauſe why I have cald and ſummoned this my preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, is, that I purpoſe to live upon mine own, and not to charge my ſubjects
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170211:45"/>but in great and urgent cauſes, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more the VVeale of themſelves, and alſo the defence of them and of this my Realme, rather than mine owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as heretofore by Commons of this Land hath beene done, and borne unto my progenitors in time of need; wherein I truſt that yee Sirs, and all the Commons of this my Land will be as tender and kinde unto me in ſuch caſes as heretofore any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons have been to any of my proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitours. And for the good will, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and true hearts that yee have borne, continued, and ſhewed to me at all times heretofore, I thanke you as heartily as I can: alſo I truſt yee will continue in time coming; for which by the grace of God I ſhall be to you as good and gracious a King, and reigne as righteouſly upon you as ever did any of my progenitors upon Commons of this my Realme in dayes paſt, and ſhall alſo in time of need apply my perſon for the VVeale and defence of you, and of this my Realme, not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my body nor life for any jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy that might happen to the ſame.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170211:46"/>
            <p>Out of this we may obſerve firſt the Kings Proteſtation to live of his owne, and not to charge his ſubjects; by which I gather he did acknowledge a certain and diſtinct property of that which way his ſubjects from that which was his own, which excludeth the right to impoſe at his will; for if that be admitted, the ſubjects property is <hi>proprietas precaria,</hi> not certaine how much of his is his owne: for that is his which the King will leave him; for there is no limit or reſtraint of the quantity, the right being admitted, but onely the Kings will.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I obſerve is this, that in charging of his ſubjects he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine himſelfe between theſe two bounds; the one, it ſhould bee in great and ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent cauſes concerning more the Weale of them, and the defence of them and his Realme, than his owne pleaſure; wherein he condemneth thoſe occaſions that grew upon exceſſe of private ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence by over great bounty, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and admitteth onely ſuch as grow by reaſon of warres, or other ſuch like publique cauſes concerning the whole
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170211:46"/>State: the other bound or limit is, that thoſe burdens ſhould be <hi>ſecundum mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem majorum,</hi> as heretofore had been done and borne by the Commons to his anceſtours in time of need.</p>
            <p>The third thing I obſerve is, that he acknowledged theſe burdens did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of their good will and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and not out of his right and prerogative; out of theſe words, that he truſted they would bee as ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and kinde to him in ſuch caſes as heretofore any Commons had been to his Progenitors: And laſtly wee may note the recompence promiſed by the King to his ſubjects, for their good wills and kindneſs, his goodneſs and grace, his juſt and righteous govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the jeopardy of his body and life for their Weale and defence Did this King aſſume to himſelfe a right to lay burdens on his ſubjects at his own will without their aſſents, that offered to buy them at his need with the price of his blood, the moſt ſacred relique in the kingdome?</p>
            <p>My fourth obſervation is that in all petitions exhibited by the Commons
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170211:47"/>in Parliament, againſt Impoſitions, the very knot of their griefe and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal cauſe of their complaint hath been expreſſed in thoſe petitions; that the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions have been without aſſent of Parliament: by which is neceſſarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, that their griefe was in point of right, not of burden.</p>
            <p>In 11.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 21. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 11 the complaint of the Impoſition of two ſhillings upon a ſacke of Wooll, two ſhillings upon a Tonne of Wine, ſix pence upon <hi>aver de pois,</hi> the cauſe of grievance expreſſed becauſe it was done <hi>Sans aſſent de Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>25 <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. Pari.</hi> 25, <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 22.</note> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 22. In a petition the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons complaine that an impoſition upon Wools was ſet by the conſent of the merchants; they pray that Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bee not made upon ſuch ſingular grants, if they be not in full Parliament; and if any ſuch grants be made, they may he held as void.</p>
            <p>17 <hi>E</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. Parl.</hi> 17. E. 3. <hi>n.</hi> 28</note> 
               <hi>n.</hi> 28. The Commons in their petition informe the King, it is againſt reaſon they ſhould be charged with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions ſet on by aſſent of Merchants, and not in Parliament.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170211:47"/>
            <p>My fifth obſervation is, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever any petition was exhibited againſt impoſitions, there was never any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect had of the quantity, but they were ever intirely abated, as well where they were ſmall, as where they were great; no requeſt ever made to make them leſs when they were great, nor excuſe made of their eaſe when they were exceeding ſmall; which ſheweth that it was not the point of bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den or exceſſe was reſpected in their complaint, but the point of meere right.</p>
            <p>25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 22.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. Parl.</hi> 25. E. 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 22.</note> Fourty ſhilling ſet an impoſition upon a ſacke of Wooll, upon complaint, all taken off, and no ſuit to be eaſed of part becauſe it was too great.</p>
            <p>36. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 26.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ibid.</hi> 38. E. 3 <hi>n.</hi> 26 21. E. 3. <hi>n.</hi> 11.</note> Three ſhillings and four pence upon a ſacke of VVool, all taken off, and no excuſe made for the ſmalneſs; for 21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 11 two ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a ſacke, two ſhillings tonnage, and ſix pence poundage.</p>
            <p>50 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 163.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. Parl.</hi> 50. E. 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 163.</note> A great complaint was made in Parliament by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons that an impoſition of a penny
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170211:48"/>was ſet upon wools for Tonage over and above the ancient due which was but a penny, and ſo the ſubject was charged with two pence.</p>
            <p>Alſo that a penny was exacted for Meſonage, which was but an halfe pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; which Impoſitions the Record doth expreſs did amount to an hundred pounds a yeere.</p>
            <p>This petty impoſition was as much ſtood upon in point of right, as the other great one of fourty ſhillings, and was taken off upon complaint in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without either juſtification or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for the ſmalneſs of it.</p>
            <p>My ſixth obſervation is, that thoſe which have adviſed the ſetting on of impoſitions without aſſent of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have been accuſed in Parliament forgiving that advice, as of a great offence in the State, and have ſuffered ſharpe cenſure and great diſgrace by it.</p>
            <p>Neither doe I finde that the quality of the perſon hath extenuated the blame, as 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3 <hi>William</hi> L. <hi>Latimer</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine to the King, and one of his private Councell, was accuſed by the Commons in Parliament of divers
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170211:48"/>deceits and extortions and miſdeeds, and among other things, that he had procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be ſet upon Wooll, Wooll-fells and other Merchandizes, new Impoſitions, to wit, upon a ſack of Wool eleven ſhillings, which the L. <hi>Latimer</hi> fought to excuſe, becauſe he had the conſent and good liking of the Merchants firſt: But judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was given againſt him that he ſhould be committed to priſon, be fined and ranſomed at the Kings will, and be put from being of the Council; and this procuring of Impoſitions to be ſet on without aſſent of Parliament is expreſly ſet down in the entry of the judgment for one of the cauſes of his cenſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Lyons</hi> a Farmer of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms in <hi>London</hi> the ſame year was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Parliament for the ſame offence;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Par.</hi> 50. E. 3. <hi>n.</hi> 17, 18, 19, 20.</note> he pleaded, he did it by the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and had anſwered the money to the Kings Chamber: Yet was condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and adjudged in Parliament to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Priſon, and all his Lands and Goods were feifed into the Kings hand; and at the laſt the hate againſt theſe authors of Impoſitions grew ſo that 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. in the ſame Parliament, a peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170211:49"/>was exhibited in Parliament to make this a capital offence; The Record is very ſhort, and therefore I will ſet it down <hi>verbatim. <q xml:lang="frm">Item prie le dit Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon que ſcit ordaine per Statute en ceſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament de touts ceux queux cy en avant mittont ou font pur lour ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler profit novels Impoſitions per lour au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie demeſn accrocheants al eux eny ul power de riens que ſoit eſtabli en Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſans aſſent de Parliament, que ils eyent judgement de vie &amp; member, &amp; de forisfacture.</q>
               </hi> To this rough Petition the King gave a milde and temperate Anſwer, <q xml:lang="frm">
                  <hi>Courre la Common ley come eſtoit al a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant uſe.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>My ſeventh Obſervation is, the ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation between 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. after this cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Parliament, and 4. <hi>Mariae</hi> almoſt two hundred years, during which time no King did attempt to impoſe without aſſent of Parliament: And yet we finde in the Parliament Rolls, that there was not one of thoſe Kings that reigned in that time, but had Impoſitions granted him upon fit occaſion by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon all Goods and Merchandizes, and at divers times during their reigns,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170211:49"/>ſometimes more, ſometimes leſs upon the Ton and pound, but ever for a time cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and indefinite; ſo the uſe of them was not given over, but the power of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing was ſo clearly and undoubtedly held to be in the Parliament, as no King went about to practice the contrary.</p>
            <p>But to this ceſſation that was of great weight and credit in our evidence, a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour was given by the other ſide to avert the inſerence made upon it, againſt the Kings right, that is, that during that time there was ſo great a Revenue grew to the Crown by double Cuſtom paid for all Merchandizes both in <hi>England</hi> and at <hi>Callis,</hi> by reaſon of an Act of Parliament made 8. <hi>H.</hi> 4. which was, that no goods ſhould be carried out of the Realm but to <hi>Callis,</hi> and by reaſon that the Merchants paid Cuſtom both there and here for the ſame goods, that in the ſeven and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth year of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, the Cuſtom of <hi>Callis</hi> was 68000. pounds the year, a great ſum, if you conſider the weight of money then, what price it bare, and by reaſon hereof Princes not delighting to charge their murmuring Subjects but when need is, being ſo amply ſupplied
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170211:50"/>otherwiſe, did not put that Prerogative in practice. To this I Anſwer, That if that were true that was urged, it might be ſome probable colour of the forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of impoſing; but I finde it quite contrary, and that by Record: For there was no ſuch reſtraint of all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities not to be tranſported to any place but <hi>Gallis,</hi> but onely Woolls, Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fells, Leather, Tinn, and Lead, that were ſtaple Wares, which by the Statute, 37, <hi>E.</hi> 3. were to be tranſported thither, and not to any other place, and the ſtaple continued at that place for the moſt part from that time untill long after, 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. but there was no double Cuſtom paid both here and there by the ſame owner: but the yearly profits of the Cuſtoms of <hi>Callais</hi> at thoſe times were ſo far ſhort of that which hath been alledged in 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. that it appeareth in an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2 printed in the book at large,
<note place="margin">27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> That the Commons do complain, That whereas in the time of <hi>E.</hi> 3. the Cuſtom of <hi>Callais</hi> was 68000 pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> at that time, which was 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. by reaſon of the ill uſage of Merchants, it was fallen to be but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170211:50"/>12000 pounds the year; ſo then there was great cauſe in that reſpect to have ſet on Impoſitions by reaſon of that great abatement of Cuſtoms, and yet it was not then offered to be done without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Parliament. But if you look a little further into the extreme neceſſities of thoſe times, you ſhall finde there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was greater cauſe to have ſtrained Prerogatives; for it appeareth in an Act of Parliament 28. <hi>H.</hi> 6. that it was then declared in Parliament by the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor and Treaſurer, who demanded re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the people for the King. both for payment of his debts, and for his yearly livelioood, that the King was then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted 372000. pounds, which now by the weight of money amounteth to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 1100000. pounds, and that his ordinary expences were more then his yearly revenue by 19000. pounds yearly: ſo if ever there was cauſe to put a King to his ſhifts, it was then; yet we ſee they did not venture to put in practice this ſuppoſed Prerogative. It further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in that Statute that the people among thoſe reaſons they alleadged why they were not able to retain the King,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170211:51"/>gave this for one, that they had ſo often granted him Tonnage and Poundage up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Merchandizes, by which it appeareth he took nothing of Merchants by impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition without grant; for if he had, no doubt they would not have ſtuck to have put him in minde of it. But I pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what became of this motion of the Chancellor and Treaſurer: The propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition had depended in Parliament many years; the effect was, the people entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the King to reſume all grants he had made from the beginning of his reign untill that time, being the twenty eighth year of his reign, excepting ſuch as were made upon conſideration valuable, that he might ſo enable himſelf by that mean by which he had impoveriſhed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and the whole Kingdom: This took effect, and the Statute of Reſumptions was thereupon made the ſame year, which Record becauſe it is not in print, and declareth theſe things with great gravity and authority: I will ſet down the very Text of it, ſo much as is mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Prayen your Commons in this your preſent Parliament aſſembled to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170211:51"/>That where you Chancellor of your Realm of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">28. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>Stat. de Reſump. in Turri Lond.</hi> not printed.</note> your Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> and many other Lords of your Council, by your high command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to your ſaid Commons, at your Parliament holden laſt at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> ſhewed and declared the State of this your Realm, which was that ye were indebted 372000 <hi>l.</hi> which is grievous, and that your livelihood in yearly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue was but 5000 <hi>l.</hi> And foraſmuch as this 5000 <hi>l.</hi> to your high and notable State to be kept, and to pay your ſaid debts, will not ſuffice: Therefore that your high Eſtate may be releived. And furthermore it was declared. That your expences neceſſary to your houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold without all other ordinary charge came to 24000 <hi>l.</hi> yearly, which exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every year in expence neceſſary over your livelihood 19000 <hi>l.</hi> Alſo pleaſeth it your Highneſs to conſider, that the Commons of your ſaid Realm be as well willing to their power, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving of your Highneſs, as ever was people to any King of your Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors that raigned in your ſaid Realm of <hi>England:</hi> But your ſaid Commons been
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170211:52"/>ſo impoveriſhed, what by taking victual to your houſhould, and other things in your ſaid Realm, and nought paid for it, and the quinzime by your ſaid Commons ſo ofren granted, and by the grant of Tunnage and Poundage, and by the grant of Subſidy upon Woolls, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grants to your Highneſs, and for lack of execution of Juſtice, that your ſaid poor Commons be full nigh deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and if it ſhould continue longer in ſuch great charge, it would not in any wiſe be had, ne born: Wherefore pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it your Highneſs, the premiſſes gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly to conſider, and that ye by the advice and aſſent of your Lords Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal, and by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this your preſent Parliament, for the conſideration of your high Eſtate, and in comfort and eaſe of your poor Commons, would take, reſume, ſeiſe and retain in your hands and poſſeſſion all honors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was very plain dealing by the people with their King, and this is the ſucceſs of the demand of ſupply and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port had in thoſe days, being required in point of gratification, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170211:52"/>or retribution for it. Thus then we have cleared this point, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. and 4. <hi>Mariae,</hi> there was not one Impoſition ſet without aſſent of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Mary</hi> in the fourth year of her reign, upon the Wars with <hi>France,</hi> ſet an Impoſition upon Clothes for this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, That the Cuſtom of Woolls was decayed, by reaſon for the moſt part they were made into Clothes, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded little Cuſtom; for that which in Wooll, paid for Cuſtom and Subſidy 40 <hi>s.</hi> made into Cloth paid but 4 <hi>s.</hi> 4 <hi>d.</hi> To recompence this by an indifferent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality, there was ſet upon a Cloth 5 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> which Impoſition did not make up the loſs ſuſtained in the Cuſtom of Wooll, by 13 <hi>s.</hi> 4 <hi>d.</hi> in 40 <hi>s.</hi> This was <hi>Juſtum,</hi> but not <hi>Juſte.</hi> This religious Prince in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed with infinite troubles in the Church and Commonwealth, and much impoveriſhed by her devotion, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the profits of the Church-lands that were in the Crown by the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, was the firſt that made digreſſion from the ſteps of her worthy Progenitors, in putting on that Impoſition without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170211:53"/>of Parliament; for that very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the loſs of Cuſtom, by turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Wooll to Clothing, came into treaty in the 24. year of <hi>E.</hi> 3. when the art of Clothing began firſt to be much practiſed in this Kingdom, and then in the recompence of the loſs ſo, ſuſtained in the decay of Cuſtom of Woolls, there was ſet upon a Cloth by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment above the olde Cuſtom, 14 <hi>d.</hi> for a Denizen, and for an Alien 21 <hi>d.</hi> This is recited in a Record in the Exchequer, 48. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot.</hi> 2. <hi>R. Theſ. in origin.</hi> But I pray you examine how this Impoſition of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was digeſted by the people. We ſee in the caſe of my Lord <hi>Dier,</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz. fol.</hi> 165. That the Merchant found great greif at it, and made exclamation and ſuit to Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to be unbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened of it:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orig. in Scac.</hi> 48. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot.</hi> 2. <hi>R. Theſ</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz. Dier fo.</hi> 165.</note> The very reaſon of their grief expreſſed in that caſe is, becauſe it was not ſet on by Parliament, but by the Queens abſolute power; So that was the ground of that complaint, the very point of right.</p>
            <p>This cauſe was referred to all the Judges, to report whether the Quimight fet on this Impoſition without aſſent
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170211:53"/>of Parliament: They divers times had conference about it, but have not yet made report for the King; which is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible preſumption, that their opinions were not for him; for it is a certain rule among us, that if a queſtion concerning the Kings Prerogative, or his profit, be referred to the Judges, if their opinions be for the King, it will be ſpeedily pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and it were indiſcretion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal it; but if there be no publication, then we make no doubt, but that their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions are either againſt the King, or at leaſt they ſtick, and give none for him.</p>
            <p>The ſame Queen <hi>Mary</hi> upon reſtraint of bringing in of French Commodities occaſioned by the then wars with <hi>France,</hi> ſet an Impoſition upon <hi>Gaſcoyn</hi> Wines, which continueth yet: So the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> by the injuſtice of that Prince was clogged with theſe two heavy Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions contrary to the right of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Acts of her Progenitors</p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſet on that upon ſweet Wines, which grew alſo upon the occaſion of the troubles with <hi>Spain.</hi> That upon Allome was none, it was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170211:54"/>a Monopoly to Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> the Cuſtomer of <hi>London,</hi> for the ingroſſing of all Allomes into his own hands, for which priviledge he gave a voluntary Impoſition upon that Commodity: It was like the priviledge granted to <hi>John Pechey</hi> of the ſweet Wines by <hi>E.</hi> 3. for which the Patentee was called into the Parliament Houſe, 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. and was there puniſhed, and his Patent taken away and cancelled.</p>
            <p>What Impoſitions have been ſet on in the Kings time, I need not expreſs, they are ſet down particularly in the Book of Rates that is in print; they are not eaſily numbered: The time for which they are raiſed is not ſhort; the Patent prefixed to that book bearing date 28. <hi>Julii,</hi> 6 <hi>Jacobi,</hi> will inſtruct you ſufficiently in that point, they be limited to the King, his Heirs and Succeſſors: which I ſuppoſe is the firſt eſtate of Fee ſimple of Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that ever man read of.</p>
            <p>My eighth and laſt Obſervation is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Tunnage and Poundage given to the King of this Realm, upon Wares and Merchandizes exported and imported, which is an Impoſition by Act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170211:54"/>and as it will appear, was given out of the peoples good will, as a very gratification to the King, to enjoyn him thereby from the deſire of voluntary Impoſitions, and to conclude him by that gift in Parliament from attempting to take any other without aſſent of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; for after the ceaſing of voluntary Impoſitions, theſe Parliamentary ones were frequent in the times of the King that ſucceeded; but they were never given but for years, with expreſs cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on how the money ſhould be beſtowed, As towards the defence of the Seas, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of Traffick, or ſome ſuch other publick cauſes: Sometimes ſpecial ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrators made by Act of Parliament, by whoſe hands the money ſhould be delivered, as 5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. in a printed Statute.
<note place="margin">5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>Rot. Par.</hi> 7. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 13. 10. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 12. 7. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 12.</note> The Rates that were given were very variable, ſometimes 2 <hi>s.</hi> Tunnage, and 6 <hi>d.</hi> Poundage as 7. <hi>R.</hi> 2. 3 <hi>s.</hi> Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and 12 <hi>d,</hi> Poundage, 10. <hi>R.</hi> 2. which grants were not to endure, the longeſt of them above a year; 18 <hi>d.</hi> Tunnage, 6 <hi>d.</hi> Poundage; in 17. <hi>R.</hi> 2.3 <hi>s.</hi> Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and 12 <hi>d.</hi> Poundage granted to <hi>H.</hi> 4. in the thirteenth year of his reign for a
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170211:55"/>certain time, in which Statute there is this clauſe, That this aide in time to come ſhould not be taken for an example to charge the Lords and Commons in manner of Subſidy, unleſs it be by the wills of the Lords and Commons, and that by a new grant to be made in full Parliament in time to come. This clauſe in good and proper conſtruction may be taken to be a very convention between the King and his people in Parliament, that he ſhould not from thenceforh, nor any of his Succeſſors ſet on Impoſitions without aſſent of Parliament. The like Impoſition was granted to <hi>H.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Par.</hi> 1. <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>n.</hi> 17.</note> 5. in the the firſt year of his reign for a ſhort time towards the defence of the Realm, and ſafeguard of the Sea, upon condition ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Act, that the Merchants Denizens, and ſtrangers coming into the Realm with their Merchandizes, ſhould be well and honeſtly uſed and handled, paying the ſaid Subſidy, as in the time of his Father, and his noble Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors Kings of <hi>England,</hi> without op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion or extortion: In the end of which Act the Commons proteſted, being bound by any grant in time to come, for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes aforeſaid.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:170211:55"/>
            <p>
               <hi>H.</hi> 6.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Par.</hi> 31. <hi>H.</hi> 6. 12. E. 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3. 6. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12. 1. E. 6. <hi>c.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Mar. c.</hi> 18. 1. <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 19. 1. <hi>Jac. c.</hi> 33.</note> in the one and thirtieth year of his reign, had Tunnage and Poundage given him for his life. <hi>E.</hi> 4. had it given him the third year of his reign, as it appeareth in a Statute 12. <hi>E</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>H.</hi> 8. in the ſixth year of his reign, and all ſince in the firſt year of their reigns have had it given them for term of their life, and being now ſo certainly ſetled, do reach further at that, from which they are in couſcience and honor excluded, by this voluntary gratification: For can any man give me a reaſon, why the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould give this Impoſition of Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and Poundage above the due Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom upon all Commodities, if the King by his Prerogative might ſet on Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons without aſſent of Parliament? and were not that a weak action in a King, to take that of his people as a benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence from them, with limitation of the ſame, and in what it ſhould be imploied, and how they will be uſed for it, and for what time he ſhall have it, which he might juſtly take without their conſents, unclogged of theſe unpleaſing incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances?</p>
            <p>The Statute of Tunnage and Poundage
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170211:56"/>made in our times, that are altogether inclined to flattery, do yet retain in them certain ſhews and rumors of thoſe antient Liberties, although indeed the ſubſtance be loſt,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Jac. c.</hi> 33.</note> as in the Statute 1. <hi>Jac. cap</hi> 33. We declare that we truſt, and have ſure confidence of his Majeſties good will towards us, in and for the keeping, and ſure defending of the Seas, and that it will pleaſe his Highneſs, that all Merchants, as well Denizens as ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers coming into this Realm, be well and honeſtly entreated and demeaned for ſuch things whereof Subſidy is granted, as they were in the time of the Kings Progenitors and Predeceſſors, without oppreſſion to them to be done. By this clauſe, as it now continueth, the true intent of this Statute appeareth to be, that there ought no other Impoſition to be laid upon Merchants beſides theſe given by this Statute, and this intention hath been well interpreted by uſe and practice from the time of <hi>E.</hi> 3. to the time of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> as before is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
            <p>Thus much of this laſt reaſon made from obſervation, and the action of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170211:56"/>our Nation. I will anſwer now ſuch main objections as have been made againſt the peoples right, and have not been touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by me <hi>obiter</hi> in my paſſage through this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>That which hath been moſt inſiſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is this, that the King by his prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Royal hath the cuſtody of the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and Ports of this Iſland, being the very gates of this Kingdom; that he in his royal function and office is onely truſted with the keys of theſe gates; that he alone hath power to ſhut them, and to open them when, and to whom he in his Princely wiſdom ſhall ſee good: that by the Law of <hi>England</hi> he may reſtrain the perſons of any from going out of the Land, or from coming into it: That he may of his own power and diſcretion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit exportation and importation of goods and Merchandizes; and out of his prerogative and preheminence, the power of impoſing, as being derivative, doth ariſe and reſult: for <hi>Cui quod majus eſt, licet, &amp; ei quod eſt minus licitum eſt:</hi> So their reaſon briefly is this; the King may reſtrain the paſſage of the perſon, and of the goods; therefore he may ſuffer
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170211:57"/>them not to paſs, but <hi>ſub modo,</hi> paying ſuch an Impoſition for his ſufferance, as he ſhall ſet upon them: For the grounds and propoſitions laid in this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, I ſhall not be much againſt any one of them, others of them muſt be qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified ere they be confeſſed; but the infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and argument made upon them, I ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny; for in it there is <hi>mutatio hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis,</hi> and a tranſition from a thing of one nature to a thing of another: As the premiſes are of a power in the King onely fiduciary, and in point of truſt and government, the concluſion infers a right of intereſt and gain; Admit the King had <hi>Cuſtodiam portuum;</hi> yet he hath but the cuſtody, which is truſt, and not <hi>Dominium utile;</hi> he hath power to open and ſhut upon conſideration of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good to the people and State, but not to make gain and benefit by it; the one is protection, the other is expilation. The Ports in their own nature are pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
<note place="margin">Portus ſunt Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lici.</note> free for all to go in and out; yet for the common good this liberty is reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the wiſdom and policy of the Prince, who is put in truſt to diſcern the times when this natural liberty ſhall be
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170211:57"/>reſtrained. In 1. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>fol.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>H.</hi> 7.10</note> 10 in the caſe of the Florentines for their Allome, the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hujſey</hi> doth write a Caſe, that in the time of <hi>E.</hi> 4. a Legate from the Pope being at <hi>Calice</hi> to come into <hi>England,</hi> it was reſolved in full Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil (as the Book ſaith) before the Lords and Judges that he ſhould not have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to come into <hi>England</hi> unleſs he would take an Oath at <hi>Calice,</hi> that he would bring nothing with him that ſhould be prejudicial to the King and his Crown.</p>
            <p>The King by the Common Law may ſend his Writ, <hi>Ne exeas regnum,</hi> to any Subject of the Realm; but the ſurmiſe of the Writ is, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Quia datum eſt nohis intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligi, quod tu verſus partes exteras abſque licentia noſtra clam deſtinas te divertere, &amp; quam plurima nobis &amp; coronae noſtrae prejudicia proſequi,</hi>
               </q> Fitzh. N. B. 85. b.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fitzh. N. B</hi> 15. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b.</hi>
               </note> So in point of Government, and common good of the Realm, he may reſtrain the perſon: But to conclude, therefore he may take money, not to reſtrain, is to ſell Government, truſt and common Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and moſt unworthy the divine Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a King. But let us compare this
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170211:58"/>power of the King in foraign affairs, with the like power he hath in Domeſtick Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. There is no queſtion but that the King hath the cuſtody of the gates of all the Towns and Cities in <hi>England,</hi> as well as all the Ports and Havens, and upon conſideration of the Weal publike may open and ſhut them at his pleaſure; as if the infection of the ſickneſs be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous in places vicine to the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> the King may command that none from thoſe places ſhall come into the City: May he therefore ſet an Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon thoſe that he ſuffereth to come into the City? So, if by reaſon of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection he forbid the bringing of Wares and Merchandizes from ſome Cities or Towns in this Kingdom to any great Fare or Mart, ſhall he therefore reſtrain the bringing of Goods thither, unleſs mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney be given him by way of Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            <p>The King in his diſcretion in point of equity, and for qualifying the rigor of the Law, may enjoyn any of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects by his Chancellor from ſuing in his Court of Common Law: May he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make a benefit by reſtraining all
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170211:58"/>from ſuit in his Courts, unleſs they pay him an Impoſition upon their Suits?
<note place="margin">2. E. 3.7.</note> In 2. <hi>E.</hi> 3. in the caſe of the Earl of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> before-cited, the King had granted unto the men of great <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> that all the Ships that arrived at the Port of <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> which conſiſted of three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ports, <hi>Great Yarmouth, Little Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> and <hi>Gerneſton,</hi> ſhould arrive all at <hi>Great Yarmouth,</hi> and at no other place within that Port. The lawfulneſs of this Patent being in queſtion in the Kings Court, it was reaſoned in the Kings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half for the upholding of the grant, as it is now, that the King had the cuſtody of the Port, he might reſtrain Merchants fron landing at all in his Kingdom: Therefore out of the ſame power might appoint where, and in what Haven they ſhould land, and no other: The Patent was demurred on in the Kings Bench, as being granted againſt the Law; but the Caſe depending, was adjourned into Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for the weight and conſequence of it, and there the Patent was condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<note place="margin">9. E. 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> and a Law made againſt ſuch and the like grants.</p>
            <p>The Preſidents that were vouched for
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170211:59"/>maintenance of this power of reſtraint in the King, were four produced almoſt in ſo many hundred years,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Par.</hi> 2. E. 1. <hi>n.</hi> 16. <hi>Rot. fin.</hi> 2. E. 1. <hi>n.</hi> 17. <hi>Ro. clauſ.</hi> 10. E. 3. <hi>dor.</hi> 31. <hi>Ro. clauſ.</hi> 17. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>in dorſ.</hi>
               </note> whereof two were in the ſecond year of <hi>E.</hi> 1. one in the tenth year of <hi>E.</hi> 3. another in the ſeventeenth year of <hi>H.</hi> 6. ſince which time we hear of none but by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as they had been uſually and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly before. To theſe I will give an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer out of themſelves, out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, out of divers Statutes, and out of the practice of the Commonwealth. The reſtaint in the time of <hi>E.</hi> 1. the one of them was to forbid the carrying of Wooll out of the Realm, the other was to forbid all Traffick with the Flemings. That of 10. <hi>E.</hi> 3. was to reſtrain the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of Ship-timber out of the Realm. That of 17. <hi>H.</hi> 6. to prohibite Traffique with the Subjects of the Duke of <hi>Burgundy.</hi> Theſe preſidents are rare, yet they have in them inducements out of publique reſpects to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; for the rule of Common Law in this caſe, I take it to be as the rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end Judge Sir <hi>Anthony Fitzherbert</hi> holds in his Writ of <hi>Ne exeas regnum in Nat.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fitzh. N. B.</hi> 85.</note> Br.</hi> that by the Common Law
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170211:59"/>any man may go out of the Kingdom, but the King may upon cauſes touching the good of the Commonwealth reſtrain any man from going by his Writ or Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and if he then go, it is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. This opinion of his is confirmed by the Book, 1. <hi>Eliz. fol.</hi> 165. <hi>Dier.</hi> 12.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dier.</hi> 1. <hi>El.</hi> 165. <hi>Dier.</hi> 13. <hi>El.</hi> 296.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>Eliz. Dier.</hi> 296. In like manner if a Subject of <hi>England</hi> be beyond ſea, and the King ſend to him to repair home, if he do it not, his Lands and goods ſhall be ſeiſed for the contempt; and this was the caſe of <hi>William de Britain</hi> Earl of <hi>Richmond,</hi> 19. <hi>E.</hi> 2. He was ſent by the King into <hi>Gaſcoyne</hi> on a meſſage,
<note place="margin">19. E. 2.</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to return, for which contempt his Goods, Chattels, Lands and Tenements were ſeiſed into the Kings hands:
<note place="margin">2, <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>P. &amp; M. Dier.</hi> 128</note> The Record is cited 2, <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Phil. &amp; Mar.</hi> in my <hi>L. Dier. fol.</hi> 128. <hi>B.</hi> and the Law there held to be ſo at that time upon a queſtion moved in the Queens behalf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt divers that being beyond the Seas refuſed to return upon commandment ſent unto them to that purpoſe: The ſame is again for Law confirmed in the Dutcheſs of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> Caſe 2 <hi>Eliz.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dier.</hi> 2. <hi>El.</hi> 176. 5 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2</note> Dier.</hi> 176. But the Common Law was
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170211:60"/>altered in this point by the Statute of 5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. by which the paſſage of all people is defended that they may not go without licence, except the Lords and other great men of the Realm, Merch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, and Souldiers: So for the Merch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, which are the people dealt withal, in the buſineſs in hand, the Common Law remaineth as it was before the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dier.</hi> 12. <hi>El.</hi> 196.</note> and ſo it was held, 12. <hi>El. Dier.</hi> 196. where the caſe was. An Engliſh Merchant being a Papiſt went over-ſea, and being there, did ſettle himſelf to remain there, for the enjoying the freedom of his conſcience: It was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved here in <hi>England,</hi> that his going without licence ſhould be a contempt, becauſe he went not to traffique as a Merchant, but for the cauſe of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: It was reſolved, no ſuch averment would be taken in this caſe, for that the very calling and vocation of being a Merchant did give him liberty to go out of the Kingdom when he would, and therefore the ſecret intent of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was not to be enquired after; <hi>Sed lex inspicit quod veriſimilius.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was in this caſe held no contempt,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170211:60"/>but at this day the Law is as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, 5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. for that Statute is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, 4. <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">4 <hi>Jac. c.</hi> 1</note> And all men what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever are now at liberty by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law to paſs out of the Realm. There is onely againſt this inconvenient liberty a Proclamation dated at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> 9. <hi>Jul</hi> 5. <hi>Jac.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proclam.</hi> 9. <hi>Jul.</hi> 5. <hi>Jac.</hi>
               </note> To the very ſame effect in point of reſtraint of paſſage with the Statute of <hi>R.</hi> 2. So the Subject is in this much the more at eaſe and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty then he was before: That his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over-ſea without licence doth not induce any forfeiture, but onely incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the cenſure of a contempt and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were to be wiſhed that ſome firm Law might be made in the caſe, both for the execution of ſo good a point of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, and for the more quiet of the State, in knowing the certainty of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the offence.</p>
            <p>This liberty and freedom of Merch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants hath been ſtrenthened and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by many notable Laws before reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as 14. <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>ſtat</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.15. <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.15. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5.18. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 3 <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>cap</hi> 5. 18 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. and divers other, and therefore though it be admitted that the King may reſtrain
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170211:61"/>perſons and goods, yet it may well be denied, that he hath power of himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone without aſſent of Parliament ſimply and indefinitely to reſtrain all traffique in general, or to ſhut up all the Havens and Ports, and to bar the vent and iſſuing of Wares and Merchandizes of the whole Kingdom, as appeareth plainly that this hath been done this three hundred years, or near thereabouts by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment onely, and that the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> made this matter of Traffique ſo tender a caſe to deal in, as that it hath ever held it a matter fit for the conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the great Council of the Kingdom, and for no other.</p>
            <p>In 11.
<note place="margin">11. E. 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3. The exportation of Woolls was prohibited by Act of Parliament, in which Statute there was this clauſe, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that by the King and his Council it be thereof otherwiſe provided: which power ſo given to the King to be uſed for the good of the Commonwealth, gave occaſion to him to abuſe it to his profit and commodity, by giving licences of tranſportation to all that would give forty ſhillings upon a Sack of Wooll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the due Cuſtom. This appeareth in
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170211:61"/>the Records in the Exchequer, 13. <hi>E</hi> 3. <hi>Rot.</hi> 2 <hi>Rem. Theſ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">13. <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>R. Theſ. rot.</hi> 2.</note> I will deſcribe the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord that you may perceive the ground of it the better, <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Rex collectoribus Cuſtumae in portu magnae Jermouth ſalutem. Quia conceſſimus dilecto &amp; fideli noſtro Hugoni de Wriothſley, quod ipſe viginti &amp; ſeptem ſaccos lanae &amp; dimid. de lanis ſuis propriis in portu praedicto carriare, &amp; eas uſque Antwerpe ad ſtapulam noſtram ibidem ducere poſſit, ſolvendo ibidem dilecto Cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co noſtro Willielmo de Northwel cuſtodi guarderobae noſtrae</hi> 40 s. <hi>pro quolibet ſacco pro cuſtuma &amp; ſubſidio inde nobis debitis, &amp;c. vobis mandamus quod praedict. Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon. dictos viginti ſeptem ſaccos lanae &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid. in portu praedicto carriaere permitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And another the ſame year.
<note place="margin">13. E. 3. <hi>rot.</hi> 12. <hi>R. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Rex collectoribus cuſtumae, &amp;c. Cum nuper or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaverimus quod paſſagium lanarum, &amp;c. apertum exiſteret, &amp; quod ſigillum noſtrum quod dicitur Coket, quod prius claudi &amp; ſub ſerra cuſtodiri mandavimus ape iretur, &amp; apertum teneretur, ideo vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis mandavimus quod ſigillum praedictum in portu praedicto aperiri, &amp; apertum tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifaciatis, &amp; omnes illos qui hujuſmodi lanas carriare &amp; ducere velint permittatis,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170211:62"/>receptis prius ab iiſdem, viz. de mercatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; aliis indigenis</hi> 40 <hi>s. de quolibet ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co lanae.</hi>
               </q> Divers other ſuch ſales of Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick occaſioned by this Parliamentary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint were made between 11. <hi>E.</hi> 3. that the reſtraint was made, and 14: <hi>E.</hi> 3. that this inconvenience being eſpied, the Sea was opened by Statute,
<note place="margin">14. E. 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. 15. E. 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2.</note> and the reſtraint removed, 14 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. 15. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>ſtat</hi> 2. and this forty ſhillings ſo exacted was complained of as an Impoſition in Parliament, and the occaſion and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect were both taken away together by Act of Parliament,
<note place="margin">14. E. 3. <hi>c.</hi> 21. <hi>ſt.</hi> 1. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp; ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>It followed in all Kings times ſithence the death of <hi>E.</hi> 3. that this opening and ſhutting of the Havens, reſtraining and enlarging of Traffick was done by Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>I will give one inſtance in the reign of every King,
<note place="margin">5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2.</note> 5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. For the paſſage of Wooll, Wooll-fells, and Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">6 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4 2. <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2.</note> 6. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. For the Traffique and Commerce with Merchants Aliens, 2. <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. For the reſtraint of Staple Commodities to places certain, and for the Traffique of the Merchants of the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170211:62"/>weſt. 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> that is enacted in Parliament which is contained in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, 17. <hi>H.</hi> 6. cited for a preſident, that is, becauſe the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> made an Ordinance whereby the Traffick of the Engliſh Nation was reſtrained, that therefore the Engliſhmen ſhould not traffick with the Subjects of the Duke of <hi>Burgundy.</hi> The ſame thing enacted upon the like occaſion, 4. <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1. 19. <hi>H.</hi> 7.
<note place="margin">4 <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1 19. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>c.</hi> 21. The importation of divers Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities forbidden as being prejudicial to the Manufactures within the Realm, 6. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.
<note place="margin">6. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> The exportation of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi> Woolls out of the Realm forbidden, 26. <hi>H.</hi> 8 <hi>cap.</hi> 10.
<note place="margin">26. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> Power is given to the King to order and diſpoſe of the Traffick of Merchants at his pleaſure, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is given, becauſe otherwiſe the Leagues and Amities with foreign Princes might be impeached by reaſon of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint made by divers ſtatutes then ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on foot, whereby it appeareth that it was not then taken to be Law, that the King had an abſolute power in himſelf to order and diſpoſe of the courſe of Traffick without help of a Statute. 2. <hi>E.</hi> 6.
<note place="margin">2 E. 6. <hi>c.</hi> 9</note> 
               <hi>cap.</hi> 9. Exportation of Leather reſtrained,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170211:63"/>1,
<note place="margin">1, <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>P. &amp; M.c.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>Ph. &amp; Mar.</hi> The exportation of Herring, Butter, Cheeſe, and other Victuals forbidden, 18. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 8. The exportation of Tallow,
<note place="margin">18. <hi>El. c.</hi> 8</note> Raw Hides, Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So in all times no uſe of Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in matters of this nature, but Acts of Parliament ſtill procured: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in mine opinion it behoveth them that do ſo earneſtly urge this argument, (the King may reſtrain Traffick, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may impoſe,) to prove better then they have done, that the King may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain Traffick of his own abſolute pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: For as the natural policy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of our Commonwealth is, we may better ſay, that is Law which is <hi>de more gentis,</hi> then that which floweth from the reaſon of any man guided by his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral notion and apprehenſion of power regal, <hi>in genere,</hi> not <hi>in indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt aſſault made againſt the right of the Kingdom, was an Objection grounded upon policy, and matter of State, as that it may ſo fall out that an Impoſition may be ſet by a foreign Prince that may wring our people, in which caſe the counterpoiſe is, to ſet on the like
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170211:63"/>here upon the Subjects of that Prince, which policy, if it be not ſpeedily execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, but ſtayed until a Parliament, may in the mean time prove vain and idle, and much damage may be ſuſtained that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not afterwards be remedied.</p>
            <p>This ſtrain of policy maketh nothing to the point of right; our rule is in this plain Commonwealth of ours, <hi>Oportet neminem eſſe ſapientiorem legibus:</hi> If there be an inconvenience, it is fitter to have it removed by a lawful means, then by an unlawful: But this is rather a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief then an inconvenience, that is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice in preſent of ſome few, but not hurtful to the Commonwealth: And it is more tolerable to ſuffer an hurt to ſome few for a ſhort time, then to give way to the breach and violation of the right of the whole Nation: For that is the true inconvenience; neither need it be ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult or tedious to have the conſent of the Parliament, if they were held as they ought, or might be; but our ſureſt guide in this will be the example of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors in this very caſe, and that in the time of one of the moſt politick Princes that ever reigned in this Kingdom, 7. <hi>H.</hi> 7.
<note place="margin">7. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:170211:64"/>
               <hi>cap.</hi> 7. you ſhall finde an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in which it was recited that the Venetians had ſet upon the Engliſh Merchants that laded Malmeſeys at <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> four duckets of gold upon a But, which in ſterling is eighteen ſhillings the But. It was therefore enacted that every Merchant ſtranger that brought Malmſey into this Kingdom ſhould pay eighteen ſhillings the But over and above the due Cuſtom uſed; this Impoſition to endure until they of <hi>Venice</hi> had ſet aſide that of four duckets the But upon the Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>Much hath been learnedly uttered up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this argument in the maintenance of the peoples right, and in anſwering that which hath been preſſed on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but my meaning is not to expreſs in this Diſcourſe all that hath or may be ſaid on either ſide, but onely to make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance ſomewhat larger of that which I my ſelf offered as my <hi>ſymbolum</hi> towards the making up of this great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning of the Commonwealth, which if it be not well audited, may in time coſt the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> very dear. My hope is of others that labored very wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170211:64"/>in this buſineſs, that they will not ſuffer their pains to die, and therefore I have forborn to enter into their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince. I will end with that ſaying of that true and honeſt Counſellor <hi>Philip Comines</hi> in his fifth book, the 18. chapter,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ph. Com. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>That it is more honorable for a King to ſay, I have ſo faithful and obedient Subjects, that they deny me nothing I demand, then to ſay, I levy what me liſt, and I have pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges ſo to do.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:170211:65"/>
            <head>After the Kings Right to Impoſe had been thorowly examined in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and there determined not to be in him alone, without aſſent of Parliament, among other Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of grievance given unto his Majeſty, this hereafter was concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Impoſitions.</head>
            <p>THe policy and conſtitution of this your Majeſties Kingdom, appropriates unto the Kings of this Realm, with aſſent of Parliament, as well the ſoveraign power of making Laws, as that of taxing or impoſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Subjects Goods or Merchandizes, wherein they juſtly have ſuch a proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as may not without their conſent be altered or changed: This is the cauſe that the people of this Kingdom, as they have ever ſhewed themſelves faithful and loving to their Kings, and ready to aid them in all their juſt occaſions with vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary contributions: ſo have they been ever careful to preſerve their own Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170211:65"/>and Rights, when any thing hath been done to prejudice or impeach the ſame: And therefore when their Princes, either occaſioned by War, or by their over-great bounty, or by any other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, have without conſent of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſet on Impoſitions either within the Land, or upon Commodities exported or imported by the Merchants, they have in open Parliament complained of it, in that it was done without their conſents, and thereupon never failed to obtain a ſpeedy and full redreſs, without any claim made by the Kings of any Power or Prerogative in that point. And though the Law of Propriety be origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and carefully preſerved by the common Laws of this Realm, which are as antient as the Kingdom it ſelf, yet thoſe famous Kings for the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and aſſurance of their loving Subjects, agreed that this old fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Right ſhould be further declared and eſtabliſhed by Act of Parliament, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is provided that no ſuch charge ſhould ever be laid upon the people without their common conſents, as may
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170211:66"/>appear by ſundry Records of former times.</p>
            <p>We therefore your Majeſties moſt humble Commons aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, following the example of this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy care of our Anceſtors, and out of our duty to thoſe for whom we ſerve, finding that your Majeſty without advice and conſent of your Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, hath lately in time of peace ſet both greater Impoſitions, and far more in number then any your noble Anceſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors did ever in time of War, do with all humility preſent this moſt juſt and neceſſary Petition unto your Majeſty, That all Impoſitions ſet without aſſent of Parliament, may be quite aboliſhed, and taken away, And that your Majeſty likewiſe in imitation of your royal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors will be pleaſed, that a Law in your time, and during this Seſſion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament may be alſo made to declare that all Impoſitions of any kinde ſet, or to be ſet upon your people, their Goods, or Merchandizes, ſave onely by common conſent in Parliament, are and ſhall be void: Wherein your Majeſty ſhall not
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170211:66"/>onely give your Subjects great ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in point of their Right, but alſo bring exceeding joy and comfort to them who now ſuffer, partly through the abating of the price of native Commodities, and partly through the raiſing of all foreign, to the overthrow of Merchants and Shipping, the cauſing a general dearth, and decay of all wealth among your people, who will be thereby no leſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged then diſabled to ſupply your Majeſty when occaſion ſhall require.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170211:67"/>
            <head>Books Printed or ſold by <hi>William Leak,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> between the two Temple gates.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>YOrks</hi> Heraldry, <hi>Fol<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> A Bible of a very fair large Roman Letter. 4</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Orlando Furioſo. fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perkins</hi> on the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wilkinſons</hi> Office of Sheriffs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Farſons</hi> Law.</item>
               <item>Mirror of Juſtice.</item>
               <item>Topicks in the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dellamans</hi> uſe of the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontal Quadrant.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wilbeys</hi> ſecond Set of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, 3, 4, 5, and 6 parts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Corderius</hi> in Engliſh.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Fulks</hi> Meteors, with Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Malthus</hi> Fire-works.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nyes</hi> Gunnery and Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cato Major</hi> with Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mel Heliconium,</hi> by <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Roſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Noſce te ipſum,</hi> by Sir <hi>John Davis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Animadverſions on <hi>Lillys</hi> Grammer.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Lazarillo de Tormes</hi> the wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hero</hi> and <hi>Leander,</hi> by <hi>George Chapman,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Marlow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Poſing of the Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Guilliams</hi> Heraldry. <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Herberts</hi> Travels. <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Man become guilty, by <hi>John Francis Senalt,</hi> and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Monmouth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aula Lucis,</hi> or the houſe of light.</item>
               <item>Chriſts Paſſion, A Tragedy written by the moſt learned <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> and Engliſhed by <hi>Geo Sand.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mathematical Recreations, with the general Horolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Ringe and the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Horizontal Dyal, by <hi>William Oughtred.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> or an accurate deſcription of Flowers and Fruit, by Sir <hi>Hugh Plat.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Solitary Devotions with man in glory, by the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:170211:67"/>reverend and holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Anſelm.</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Book of Martyrs. <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Adams</hi> on <hi>Peter, fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Willet</hi> on <hi>Geneſis</hi> and <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus. fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elton</hi> on the <hi>Coloſſians. fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Theſeveral opinions of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry learned Antiquaries, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. Juſtice <hi>Doddridge,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ager, Francis Tate, William Cambden,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph Holland,</hi> touching the Antiquity, Power, Order, State, Manner, perſons and Proceedings of the high Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Idiot, in four Book.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Exercitatio Scholaſtica.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Life and Reign of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. by the Lord <hi>Herbert.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>France</hi> painted to the life, the ſecond Edition. 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sken de ſignificatione ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>The Fort Royal of Holy Scripture, by <hi>J. H.</hi> the third Edition. 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Callis</hi> learned Readings on the Stat. 21. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. chap. 5. of Shewers.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>PLAYES,</head>
               <item>Philaſter.</item>
               <item>The Wedding.</item>
               <item>The Holleder.</item>
               <item>The Merchant of <hi>Venice.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſtrange diſcovery.</item>
               <item>Maids Tragedy.</item>
               <item>King and no King.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Othello,</hi> the Moor of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The grateful Servant.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
